<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ad | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/ad/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-22T01:56:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A business wants to see the light]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2011/02/business-wants-to-see-light/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-03T10:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2011/02/business-wants-to-see-light</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: justify;">You may remember <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2010/12/kirikou-open-electricity-monitor.html">my last post</a> on this blog. I was raising money to fund my prototype of an energy monitor connected to the cloud via WiFi. The crowdfundraising was a success (probably thanks to some of you), now that 95% of the components arrived I had the monitor assembled and the sketch running. A few technical problems are to be overcome (please check the forum and see if you can help), and the business plan is taking shape.</div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<br /></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">Yes, exactly: business plan :) Trystan, the other founders and myself would love to see a few small businesses based on the concept of open source hardware, in other words we would like to see some people making money with this system. Moreover, we would like to see a network of these businesses co-existing in a constructive symbiose to drive the wheel of development on a wide scale.</div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<br /></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">We are probably too much influenced with the amazing success story of the <a href="http://reprap.org/wiki/Main_Page">RepRap</a> project, and so what? I personally believe there could be fantastic things evolving around the open energy monitor concept.</div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<br /></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">To start a business is a very hard task, definitely too much for one person, even if you work 24 hours you can not be good at both business development and product development, this is why I decided to get help from another person to sail this boat: I think with the help of one or two other persons we can launch a small but promising and ambitious startup that produces around 30-50 energy monitoring systems per month. My technical skills are modest, I can not pretend to be an engineer, this is why I will find the help of a technic freak priceless.</div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<br /></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">I posted this <a href="http://www.adafruit.com/jobs/job/97/energy-monitoring-engineertinkerer-at-simple-tech-engineering/">little ad on adafruit industries</a>, it is not a job description, and can be part or full time, up to you. The most important is that if you show interest we can talk about it and see where we go from there.</div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<br /></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<br /></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;"><meta charset="utf-8" /><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_J5YXCS95cgQ/TUqBv_WunmI/AAAAAAAAAMg/8R-9Z3TMiYY/s1600/Job.png"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_J5YXCS95cgQ/TUqBv_WunmI/AAAAAAAAAMg/8R-9Z3TMiYY/s320/Job.png" border="0" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5569406550657637986" style="display: block; margin-top: 0px; margin-right: auto; margin-bottom: 10px; margin-left: auto; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 320px; height: 229px; " /></a></div>
<div>
<br /></div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
