<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: application | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/application/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-27T11:17:40+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Electrical Supply Line Vault]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/06/emonpi-vrms-line-fault/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-03T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/06/emonpi-vrms-line-fault</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week my home emonPi energy monitor came in handy to help diagnose an electrical supply fault.</p>

<p>A neighbour alerted me that her lights were flickering and internet router was dropping offline. At the time I was doing some DIY and had noticed the power drill I was using change speed erratically. I had presumed it was my drill about the give up the ghost.</p>

<p>I checked the Emoncms graph on my emonPi energy monitor and noticed that VRMS was well out of spec at about 150V (we usually get 230V*) and occasionally jumping up to almost 300V! The electrical company was alerted and the fault was traced back to a frayed conductor on our street. I helped the electrical contractors view the real-time VRMS value to confirm the fault was fixed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/vrms.png" alt="VRMS Fault" /></p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="notes-on-mains-voltage-limits">* Notes on Mains Voltage Limits</h2>

<p>The standard domestic mains supply for Europe is 230 V ± 10%, giving a lower limit of 207 V and an upper limit of 253 V. It is permissible under BS 7671 to have a voltage drop within the installation of 5%, which would give a lower limit of 195.5 V.
The UK standard prior to harmonization was 240 V ± 6%, giving an upper limit of 254.4 V.</p>

<p>Although the UK nominal standard is now 230 V, the supply system has not generally been adjusted, and the voltage centers around 240 V.</p>

<p>Thanks to Robert Wall for summarizing the rather convoluted standards surrounding UK grid voltages.</p>

<p>All of Europe, Africa, Asia, Australia, New Zealand and most of South America, use a supply that is within 6% of 230 V</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mains_electricity_by_country">Mains Electricity by Country (Wikipedia)</a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
