<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: media | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/media/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-26T02:06:36+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Low carbon energy film featuring OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/01/french-low-carbon-energy-film-featuring/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-01T11:23:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/01/french-low-carbon-energy-film-featuring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago we were lucky to be contacted by a French film team wanting to feature OpenEnergyMonitor as part of a film about low carbon energy. The film “ACHIEVING 2050 I OPTIMIZE ENERG” aired in November this year.<br /><br />The film can be watched online here (in French), the part featuring us starts at 28min in:</p>

<!--more-->

<p><br /><br /><a href="http://video.capatv.com/index.php?Lien=ca608d1a258e4de2cf9f26210711518bbc7467fa">http://video.capatv.com/index.php?Lien=ca608d1a258e4de2cf9f26210711518bbc7467fa</a><br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-R7JmmEn0nek/VobJQJ8iUsI/AAAAAAABllI/n8QWj0DDKDU/s1600/CXduRhVWEAA_hRm.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="640" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-R7JmmEn0nek/VobJQJ8iUsI/AAAAAAABllI/n8QWj0DDKDU/s640/CXduRhVWEAA_hRm.png" width="578" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><br />Here is the blurb translated from French:<br /><br /><i>“Globally 40% of greenhouse gas emissions are caused by the production of electricity required for industry, heating and everyday life. More than two thirds of the electricity is actually produced in thermal power plants from fossil fuels, ie coal, gas or oil, which releases large amounts of CO2. This production increasing with the construction of new power plants in emerging countries. </i><br /><i><br /></i><i>By 2050, with 3 billion additional inhabitants, the electricity demand will still grow enormously. So how do you reverse to generate electricity without emitting greenhouse gases to limit global warming to 2 ° C by the end of the century?</i></p>

<p> &lt;/i&gt;<br /><i><br /></i><i>We started to meet those have opted for autonomy through renewable energies, which have learned to control and optimize power consumption. This is the case in Britain, where the communities of common shiner is to succeed the challenge of energy independence, with the implementation of wind and electricity production from bio-methane from swine manure. Everywhere Worldwide solutions are found to save and optimize energy. Some, like in Boston in the United States live in houses positive energy, which produce more energy than they consume through “smart habitats.” Other innovate by using waste heat from factories, which can heat homes. Each in their own way, these precursors are revolutionizing existing models of energy production, to build a world more respectful of the planet.”</i></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We Won! Daily Post Business Award 2013 - Green Award Category ]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/01/we-won-daily-post-business-award-2013/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T22:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/01/we-won-daily-post-business-award-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-9YIm0l2TE78/Usra6Ww1kJI/AAAAAAAAsiY/geWpddZIM1c/s1600/DailyPostBusiness+Award+winner.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-9YIm0l2TE78/Usra6Ww1kJI/AAAAAAAAsiY/geWpddZIM1c/s1600/DailyPostBusiness+Award+winner.jpg" height="320" width="252" /></a></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><br /></div>
<p>We have been lucky enough to be awarded winner of the Green Award category in the Daily Post Business Awards 2013. The Daily Post is a regional (North West Wales) newspaper, the Green Award was sponsored this year by Windpower Wales. The award was announced at the end of last year, I resisted posting about it until we got our hands on the video that was made about us.<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-CzJ1Zr-KHsI/Uvu4dbctpaI/AAAAAAAAt14/N-0kXuwlIZg/s1600/IMG_20140206_103538.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-CzJ1Zr-KHsI/Uvu4dbctpaI/AAAAAAAAt14/N-0kXuwlIZg/s1600/IMG_20140206_103538.jpg" height="300" width="400" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Trystan being interviewed by Daily Post newspaper, <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2014/02/weve-made-local-newspaper.html">read the article here</a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />Winning the award was very unexpected for us, we feel very humbled. It goes without saying that it would not be possible for us to be doing what we do if it was not for the work of many others. As always with open-source it feels like we are standing on the shoulders of lots of other projects. A big thank you to everyone who has contributed to the project in some way and or bought items from the shop.<br /><br />Given the nature of an online collaborative project such as OpenEnergyMonitor much of our day-to-day communications and business is conducted online; it’s great that what we are doing is being recognised locally. Trystan and I are very proud to be able to live and work in Snowdonia, North Wales. We’re both welsh speakers and were brought up locally. Our website <a href="http://megni.co.uk/">http://megni.co.uk</a> has a couple of photos I’ve taken while out climbing and walking in the Snowdonia mountains as well as an overview of the OpenEnergyMonitor system.<br /><br />Megni (which means ‘monitoring energy’ in Welsh) is the name of our business which runs the OpenEnergyMonitor shop. We’re keen to make the distinction between Megni and OpenEnergyMonitor since we don’t take claim for all OpenEnergyMonitor developments: the .org website, open-source hardware, software and documentation is all separate from the business. Megni is a partnership between Trystan Lea and myself (Glyn Hudson); we now have a couple of friends Ynyr Edwards and Gwil Noble working with us helping with shop fulfillment, support requests and ongoing development.<br /><br />This award ended 2013 on a high for us, it’s been a very exciting few months launching new<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2013/11/new-hardware-is-in-shop-and-starting-to.html"> pre-assembled hardware units</a> and moving into a<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2013/10/new-office-space-and-new-units.html"> new office / lab space</a>. Let’s hope 2014 is just as awesome! We have lots of exciting plans for this year, high on the list is starting to <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2013/12/emoncms-early-heating-control-demo.html">move into the control of appliances</a> and general polishing of the energy monitoring system. <br /><br />Here’s a short video which was made for the event, it’s got some nice shots of the hardware and our new lab:<br /><br /><object height="360" width="640"><param name="movie" value="//www.youtube.com/v/GRmqA2bv22A?hl=en_GB&amp;version=3&amp;rel=0" />&lt;/param&gt;<param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" />&lt;/param&gt;<param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always" />&lt;/param&gt;<embed src="//www.youtube.com/v/GRmqA2bv22A?hl=en_GB&amp;version=3&amp;rel=0" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="640" height="360" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" />&lt;/embed&gt;</object> <br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;<br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
