<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: open source | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/open-source/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-25T14:20:11+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing KiCad PCB]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/10/testing-kicad-pcb/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-25T18:54:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/10/testing-kicad-pcb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are always a fan of using open-source software wherever possible. A few years ago I briefly attempted to use open-source KiCad and gEDA PCB CAD software but found them very limiting, clumsy and buggy.<br /><br />Recently there have been a raft of shiny looking browser based PCB design tools such as <a href="http://circuitmaker.com/">Circuit Maker</a> and <a href="https://upverter.com/">Upverter</a>, these look very interesting; the online collaborative development opportunities are obvious and linking into the <a href="https://blog.octopart.com/archives/2014/09/introducing-the-common-parts-library">OctoPart’s live component pricing, standard part library</a> and <a href="https://blog.octopart.com/archives/2014/09/bom-tool-real-time-collaboration">BOM management tools</a> could be a big time saver at the manufacturing stage. Maybe online tools will be the future, however I am a little reserved about having designs locked into a closed online platform.<br /><br />In particular I have been keeping a close eye on KiCad developments after I heard CERN had got involved in the development. I was very impressed watching this video showing the newly developed KiCad intelligent semi-auto router in action:<br /><br />&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/CCG4daPvuVI" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; <br />I think it’s time I gave KiCad another try! Today I managed to install KiCad and put together the RFM12Pi schematic and layout the board. Here’s my experience:<br /><br />I wanted the latest build to get the shiny new features, so I installed the development branch by adding the PPA to Ubuntu:<br /><br />http://ppa.launchpad.net/js-reynaud/ppa-kicad/ubuntu<br /><br />I installed KiCad build dated 16th July on 32-bit Ubuntu 14.04<br /><br />I found I needed to add the line “<i>export KIGITHUB=”https://github.com/KiCad”;</i>” to my ~/.profile file to get rid of cannot find github footprint errors when running CvPCB (the program in KiCad which links the schematic parts to PCB footprints)<br /><br />I followed the <a href="http://youtube.com/user/contextualelectronic/playlists">fantastic video tutorials from Contextual Electronics</a> to help me get started.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-VGCAtJX3smQ/VEvtnfmCwTI/AAAAAAAA-Uk/eFW5ZB3wWsk/s1600/Selection_002.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-VGCAtJX3smQ/VEvtnfmCwTI/AAAAAAAA-Uk/eFW5ZB3wWsk/s1600/Selection_002.png" height="362" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;1. KiCad Schematic Editor, net list must be manually exported to move to the next setp&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-CX3B8v8OQpQ/VEvtq158i_I/AAAAAAAA-U8/o_9ReXUxvFo/s1600/Cvpcb%2B(2014-jul-16%2BBZR%2Bunknown)-product%2B%2B-home-glyn-Documents-KiCad_test-KiCad_test.net_001.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-CX3B8v8OQpQ/VEvtq158i_I/AAAAAAAA-U8/o_9ReXUxvFo/s1600/Cvpcb%2B(2014-jul-16%2BBZR%2Bunknown)-product%2B%2B-home-glyn-Documents-KiCad_test-KiCad_test.net_001.png" height="232" width="400" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;2. Linking schematic parts to PCB footprints&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-3IkhKZipylI/VEvtnigY9CI/AAAAAAAA-Uo/QmM0GSC83VM/s1600/Selection_003.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-3IkhKZipylI/VEvtnigY9CI/AAAAAAAA-Uo/QmM0GSC83VM/s1600/Selection_003.png" height="360" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;3. Board layout the new interactive router was great (see video above)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-dZn9nSbAuS4/VEvvCcN1NCI/AAAAAAAA-VE/FpWmyjWZNFU/s1600/Selection_005.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-dZn9nSbAuS4/VEvvCcN1NCI/AAAAAAAA-VE/FpWmyjWZNFU/s1600/Selection_005.png" height="320" width="191" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;New router options&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />Update: the finished Kicad RFM2Pi V2.7 design is up on github:&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;https://github.com/openenergymonitor/Hardware/tree/master/RFM2Pi/board/KiCad_RFM12Pi%20V2.7&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;div&gt;Obviously we have considerable lock-in to EAGLE PCB with our historic designs and learning a new software tool is always going to be a slow and slightly frustrating process, however I’m quite impressed that after about 5hrs I think I’m got the hang of basic KiCad functions. I will seriously consider using KiCad for new designs in the future. I think the increased effort will be worthwhile to enable us to be using a fully open-source bit of design software to design open-hardware, what do you think?&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Thinks I liked about KiCad:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Interactive router, very impressed with this. Big time saver&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;More intuitive setup of default track widths and net classes &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;How net and pin names are displayed in the layout editor &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;How schematic symbols and PCB footprints are handled as separate entities, more intuitive than Eagle IMHO  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;Thinks I miss moving from Eagle:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Have a live link between schematic and PCB, KiCad requires exporting and re-importing a new netlist each time there is a change in schematic&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;There are more ready made parts in Eagle libraries then there are <a href="https://github.com/kicad">KiCad part libraries</a>, but I’m sure this will change. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Being able to highlight all tracks on a particular net by selecting a wire on the schematic (maybe I’ve just not found this feature yet in KiCad?)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A right to build: An open approach to housing provision: self-provision]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/08/a-right-to-build-open-approach-to/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-26T16:35:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/08/a-right-to-build-open-approach-to</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><br />&lt;div style="text-align: right;"&gt;<a href="http://issuu.com/alastairparvin/docs/2011_07_06_arighttobuild" style="clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;"><img alt="http://issuu.com/alastairparvin/docs/2011_07_06_arighttobuild" border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-PkHatNxkQjM/U_yz8GedycI/AAAAAAAAGNA/fzqMeqCVSfc/s1600/arighttobuild.png" height="320" width="241" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;A right to build is a booklet written by <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/alastair_parvin_architecture_for_the_people_by_the_people">Alaistair Parvin</a> of (00 and <a href="http://wikihouse.cc/">Wikihouse</a>), David Saxby, Cristina Cerulli and Tatjana Schneider that outlines a clear and comprehensive vision for how a self-provision approach to housing could be the best way to tackle the UK housing crisis while delivering higher quality, higher performance low energy housing. <br /><br />Its a deeply inspiring vision of the potential power that empowering, distributive, open ways of doing things, that gives us all agency, to participate in solving problems like climate change can have.<br /><br />‘A right to build’ starts by making an observation that we have become accustomed to an assumption that progress in production is the expansion of mass-produced goods, built by professionals and mass-consumed by citizens, a legacy of the industrial revolution, but far from progress the report provides a strong case that the large house builder model has actually resulted in a deterioration in the quality of housing when measured against modern examples of self-provision and self-build.<br /><br />Driven by a combination of massive house price inflation over the last 40 years and the associated treatment of homes increasingly as financial assets, the incentives for higher quality housing has been sidelined with financial values being pursued over use value.<br /><br /><b>Who should build?</b><br /><br /><i>“The question is not ‘What homes do we need?, but rather ‘Who should build them?’ “ - A right to build.</i><br /><b><br />Self-provision</b><br /><br />Self provision of housing is a spectrum of models, the most common characteristic is that the first owners act as the client commissioning their own home. Beyond this there is a varying degree of involvement. From contracting out all of the work or doing a lot of the work yourself (self-build).<br /><br /><b>Advantages to self-provision:</b><br /><br />Self provision fundamentally transforms the kind of houses and neighbourhoods that get built:<br />&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Designed for long term use-value, higher quality: affordability, generosity, sustainability, flexibility, community. Form of production that is structured around valuing those things. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Increased affordability. Overall cost often a third less and can be even less if you use your own ‘sweat equity’ (do a proportion of the building work yourself). &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;More innovative, more likely to explore more innovate architectural styles and newer and higher performing low energy building materials. More likely to create spaces that lead to further innovation: workshops, garages.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;Self-provided housing is intrinsically more capable of delivering better outcomes because the developer is the user.<br /><br /><b>Removing barriers to participation</b><br /><br /><i>“The most challenging, but most crucial aspect of scaling the self-provided housing sector is not just increasing capacity for the current self-providing demographic, but coming up with innovative models which lower the economic threshold for participation.”</i><br /><br />It mentions the Walter Segal system for self-build conceived in the 1960s and 1970s which is one historical example of an attempt to do this.<br />&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Used an affordable, widely available and easy-to- work with material: timber.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lowered the skill-threshold for self-builders. With a bit of basic training and common sense, even those who didn’t have mainstream construction skills could put together a Walter Segal house.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;Alaistair Parvin and 00’s more recent project is <a href="http://wikihouse.cc/">wikihouse</a> an open source low energy affordable home construction system that makes use of modern CNC manufacturing methods and self assembly on site. Wikihouse has a growing global community of people developing design’s, sharing them openly online and prototyping these housing solutions. Like Walter Segal’s system the aim is to lower the economic threshold for participation both by creating an open source self-build system and all the learning resources and collaboration, peer to peer support systems that can come from online open source projects. <br /><br />Towards the end of the report a very good point is made about the mistaken attitude and opportunity lost that often classifies the professional-citizen relationship:<br /><i><br />“Thirdly, by treating citizens only as passive users of a finished commodity provided by professionals, it can actually decrease the usefulness and quality of that commodity (as this booklet has argued in the case of housing) and decrease also the self-reliance and mutual support within communities. Citizens can be treated as passive, rather than active users, and their potential value can be overlooked. As the New Economics Foundation wrote in their 2008 pamphlet on the subject:</i><br /><br /><i>“The reason today’s problems seem so intractable is that public services, and technocratic management systems, have become blind to the most valuable resource they possess: their own clients and the neighbourhoods around them. When these assets are ignored or deliberately side-lined, then they atrophy.””</i><br /><br />This is arguably one of the key principles of open source which is perhaps one of the clearest definitions of a system that enables this, a phrase commonly found in open source projects is that this project is open for everyone. Its open to everyone to make build, improve, modify, share, learn. <br /><br />By treating fellow citizens as co-developers, fellow self-providers as equal contributors rather than passive consumers it unlocks this capacity that we all have.<br /><br />Read the A Right to build here <a href="http://issuu.com/alastairparvin/docs/2011_07_06_arighttobuild">http://issuu.com/alastairparvin/docs/2011_07_06_arighttobuild</a><br /><br />Alaistair Parvin’s TED talk: <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/alastair_parvin_architecture_for_the_people_by_the_people">http://www.ted.com/talks/alastair_parvin_architecture_for_the_people_by_the_people</a><br /><br />Wikihouse: <a href="http://wikihouse.cc/">http://wikihouse.cc/</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We Won! Daily Post Business Award 2013 - Green Award Category ]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/01/we-won-daily-post-business-award-2013/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T22:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/01/we-won-daily-post-business-award-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-9YIm0l2TE78/Usra6Ww1kJI/AAAAAAAAsiY/geWpddZIM1c/s1600/DailyPostBusiness+Award+winner.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-9YIm0l2TE78/Usra6Ww1kJI/AAAAAAAAsiY/geWpddZIM1c/s1600/DailyPostBusiness+Award+winner.jpg" height="320" width="252" /></a></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><br /></div>
<p>We have been lucky enough to be awarded winner of the Green Award category in the Daily Post Business Awards 2013. The Daily Post is a regional (North West Wales) newspaper, the Green Award was sponsored this year by Windpower Wales. The award was announced at the end of last year, I resisted posting about it until we got our hands on the video that was made about us.<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-CzJ1Zr-KHsI/Uvu4dbctpaI/AAAAAAAAt14/N-0kXuwlIZg/s1600/IMG_20140206_103538.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-CzJ1Zr-KHsI/Uvu4dbctpaI/AAAAAAAAt14/N-0kXuwlIZg/s1600/IMG_20140206_103538.jpg" height="300" width="400" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Trystan being interviewed by Daily Post newspaper, <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2014/02/weve-made-local-newspaper.html">read the article here</a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />Winning the award was very unexpected for us, we feel very humbled. It goes without saying that it would not be possible for us to be doing what we do if it was not for the work of many others. As always with open-source it feels like we are standing on the shoulders of lots of other projects. A big thank you to everyone who has contributed to the project in some way and or bought items from the shop.<br /><br />Given the nature of an online collaborative project such as OpenEnergyMonitor much of our day-to-day communications and business is conducted online; it’s great that what we are doing is being recognised locally. Trystan and I are very proud to be able to live and work in Snowdonia, North Wales. We’re both welsh speakers and were brought up locally. Our website <a href="http://megni.co.uk/">http://megni.co.uk</a> has a couple of photos I’ve taken while out climbing and walking in the Snowdonia mountains as well as an overview of the OpenEnergyMonitor system.<br /><br />Megni (which means ‘monitoring energy’ in Welsh) is the name of our business which runs the OpenEnergyMonitor shop. We’re keen to make the distinction between Megni and OpenEnergyMonitor since we don’t take claim for all OpenEnergyMonitor developments: the .org website, open-source hardware, software and documentation is all separate from the business. Megni is a partnership between Trystan Lea and myself (Glyn Hudson); we now have a couple of friends Ynyr Edwards and Gwil Noble working with us helping with shop fulfillment, support requests and ongoing development.<br /><br />This award ended 2013 on a high for us, it’s been a very exciting few months launching new<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2013/11/new-hardware-is-in-shop-and-starting-to.html"> pre-assembled hardware units</a> and moving into a<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2013/10/new-office-space-and-new-units.html"> new office / lab space</a>. Let’s hope 2014 is just as awesome! We have lots of exciting plans for this year, high on the list is starting to <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2013/12/emoncms-early-heating-control-demo.html">move into the control of appliances</a> and general polishing of the energy monitoring system. <br /><br />Here’s a short video which was made for the event, it’s got some nice shots of the hardware and our new lab:<br /><br /><object height="360" width="640"><param name="movie" value="//www.youtube.com/v/GRmqA2bv22A?hl=en_GB&amp;version=3&amp;rel=0" />&lt;/param&gt;<param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" />&lt;/param&gt;<param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always" />&lt;/param&gt;<embed src="//www.youtube.com/v/GRmqA2bv22A?hl=en_GB&amp;version=3&amp;rel=0" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="640" height="360" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" />&lt;/embed&gt;</object> <br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;<br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open source sailing technology to clean up oil spills]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2012/07/open-source-sailing-technology-to-clean/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-26T10:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2012/07/open-source-sailing-technology-to-clean</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<object height="374" width="526"><param name="movie" value="http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf" /><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" /><param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always" /><param name="wmode" value="transparent" /><param name="bgColor" value="#ffffff" /><param name="flashvars" value="vu=http://video.ted.com/talk/stream/2012S/Blank/CesarHarada_2012S-320k.mp4&amp;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/CesarHarada_2012S-embed.jpg&amp;vw=512&amp;vh=288&amp;ap=0&amp;ti=1499&amp;lang=en&amp;introDuration=15330&amp;adDuration=4000&amp;postAdDuration=830&amp;adKeys=talk=cesar_harada_a_novel_idea_for_cleaning_up_oil_spills;year=2012;theme=a_greener_future;theme=ocean_stories;theme=inspired_by_nature;theme=talks_from_ted_fellows;event=TEDxSummit;tag=global+issues;tag=oceans;tag=open-source;&amp;preAdTag=tconf.ted/embed;tile=1;sz=512x288;" /><embed src="http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf" pluginspace="http://www.macromedia.com/go/getflashplayer" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" wmode="transparent" bgcolor="#ffffff" width="526" height="374" allowfullscreen="true" allowscriptaccess="always" flashvars="vu=http://video.ted.com/talk/stream/2012S/Blank/CesarHarada_2012S-320k.mp4&amp;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/CesarHarada_2012S-embed.jpg&amp;vw=512&amp;vh=288&amp;ap=0&amp;ti=1499&amp;lang=en&amp;introDuration=15330&amp;adDuration=4000&amp;postAdDuration=830&amp;adKeys=talk=cesar_harada_a_novel_idea_for_cleaning_up_oil_spills;year=2012;theme=a_greener_future;theme=ocean_stories;theme=inspired_by_nature;theme=talks_from_ted_fellows;event=TEDxSummit;tag=global+issues;tag=oceans;tag=open-source;&amp;preAdTag=tconf.ted/embed;tile=1;sz=512x288;" /></object>
<p><br /><br />What a great explanation of the importance of open hardware for developing environmental technology and the right conception of business where purpose comes first and profit is there to make the purpose happen rather than technology as a means to make profit, excellent!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open source hardware and the free rider dilemna]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2012/04/open-source-hardware-and-free-rider/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-11T18:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2012/04/open-source-hardware-and-free-rider</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div dir="ltr" style="text-align: left;" trbidi="on">I wrote a post on my personal blog about using content from open source projects in general and the Open Energy monitor in particular. Here is an extract of it:<br /><br /><br /><blockquote class="tr_bq">There are now more than 960 registered members in the community, not all of them are active and quite a few contribute actively to the development of the project. But does that mean that the others are just passive members?&nbsp;<a data-mce-href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_rider_problem" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_rider_problem" style="color: #1b8be0; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.625; text-decoration: none;" target="_blank" title="Free rider wikipedia">free riders</a>? is that fair?<br />I started toying with the idea of using an arduino to monitor electricity consumption about two years ago, and I found out that someone else (Trystan and Glyn and quite a few others) already started developing that idea and sharing their work and findings online. Sharing their work and code online does not only&nbsp;<strong style="color: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.625;">save other people</strong>&nbsp;(actually humanity in general)&nbsp;<strong style="color: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.625;">a lot of time and effort</strong>, but it also allows for a much wider scope of fellow tinkerers to&nbsp;<strong style="color: inherit; font-style: inherit; line-height: 1.625;">review and improve that work</strong>.</blockquote><div style="color: #333333; line-height: 24px; margin-bottom: 1.625em; text-align: -webkit-auto;"><span style="font-family: Times, 'Times New Roman', serif;">You can read the post <a href="http://www.blogbouha.com/2012/04/oshw-free-rider-dilemna/">on my blog</a>.</span></div></div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
