<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: arduino | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/arduino/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2022-04-12T16:21:24+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developing for Arduino remotely on a Raspberry Pi]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/12/developing-for-arduino-remotely-on/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T22:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/12/developing-for-arduino-remotely-on</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found myself tonight requiring the ability to develop for Arduino remotely on a Raspberry Pi. The use case is connecting an Arduino Uno to a Raspberry Pi to receive data from my <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/beehive/v2">Bee Hive Temperature Monitor</a> setup. The Arduino posts data received from the Bee Monitor as a serial string onto ttyUSB0, <a href="https://github.com/openenergymonitor/EmoncmsPythonLink">EmoncmsPythonLink</a> script is used to post the data to the emoncms server running locally on the <a href="http://emoncms.org/site/docs/raspberrypihdd">Raspberry Pi with the file system on an external hard drive</a>. The Pi also has an RFM12Pi fitted receiving data from an emonTx and a couple of emonTH’s<br /><br />I wanted to be able to access the Arduino, and upload a new sketch to fix bugs etc remotely since I will not always have local access to the system.<br /><br />I came across a great Arduino command line build environment called inotool<br /><br /><a href="http://inotool.org/">http://inotool.org/</a><br /><br /><br /><i>$ sudo apt-get update </i><br /><i>$ sudo apt-get install arduino</i><br /><i>$ sudo apt-get install python-dev&amp;&amp;python-setuptools</i><br /><i>$ git clone git://github.com/amperka/ino.git</i><br /><i>$ cd ino</i><br /><i>$ sudo python setup.py install</i><br />&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;if you want to use ino’s built in serial terminal<br /><br /><i>$ sudo apt-get install picocom</i><br /><br />&lt;div&gt;to exit picocom serial [CTRL + A] followed by [CTRL + X]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<i>$ ino init -t blink      # initiates a project using “blink” as a template, copy libraries into </i>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<i>$ ino build               # compiles the sketch, creating .hex file (default Arduino uno -m atmega328 for duemilanove)</i>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<i>$ ino upload             # uploads the .hex file</i>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<i><br /></i>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;The setup works well, opening the port on the router I can now ssh into the Pi and upload new sketches to the Arduino from anywhere on the web,&lt;/div&gt;<br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kirikou: an open electricity monitor]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2010/12/kirikou-open-electricity-monitor/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-20T00:40:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2010/12/kirikou-open-electricity-monitor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: left;">Hello everyone,</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">This is my first contribution to this blog after months of reading it :)</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">I am Amin, I study a Bsc. of "<a href="http://www.tu-cottbus.de/fakultaet4/de/environment/">Environmental and Resource Management</a>" at the BTU, and I am currently doing an internship at the technical department at <a href="http://www.wagner-solar.com/wagnerEN/?ref=/wagnerDE/">Wagner und Co. Solartechnik</a> in Marburg.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">My main task in this internship is to dimension and design photovoltaic systems for our clients overseas, and I could not help but notice how pricy the existing monitoring solutions are: more than 400 euros for a box that monitors your inverter's production and makes the data available on the internet. So I started thinking about building a system that does that for a very "affordable" cost. And since I have caught the Arduino virus for quite some time (Wired magazine's fault), I started to think about making an Arduino-based photovoltaic plant monitor, this is how I found the open energy monitor initiative.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">Months of browsing and thinking made this little idea grow in my head like a good cancer, and talking to people about it generated mostly positive feedback.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">I am now determined to launch a commercial product (<a href="http://diydrones.com/">DIY-Drones</a> business model, more or less) that is based on the open energy monitor. This device, which I name for the moment Kirikou, will monitor the mains AC that comes from the meter to the distribution box in each building, plus 5 to 20 sub-circuit consumers. It will not require the intervention of an electrician (clip CT's). It will send the data to Pachube or Google Charts via Wifi. And it will cost 200-240 euros per unit.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">Quite an ambitious target I know, but with the help and support of the inventors, the community and some other people, I am confident that I can make it take off. <a href="http://blog.ponoko.com/index.php?s=%22ten+rules+for+maker%22">Open source hardware businesses</a> started to pop up like mushrooms the last years, and that's fantastic! It is only fair to share the knowledge about things, it is a win-win situation for everyone and I really hope to see many businesses based on the open energy monitor.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">There are also some unconventional ways to get it started, like these sponsoring programs that help entrepreneurs get on their feet in the beginning. A very good friend sent me this link to the Zurich HUB fellowship, and I applied.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">I thought it would be in the spirit of the competition to get a community involved, and I created this Ulule page (screenshot below) to raise 120 euros to build my electricity monitor based on the Blackwidow board.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://www.ulule.com/kirikou-an-open-source-electricity-monitor/"><img src="http://sphotos.ak.fbcdn.net/hphotos-ak-snc4/hs1168.snc4/151044_10150324187775461_904875460_15862761_726884_n.jpg" /></a></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">I am really excited to start this adventure with the support of a community, I believe that we could develop and spread this together.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">I believe the first step should be to get more organized and communicate more efficiently on the technical choices and so on.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">Your feedback, comments, criticism is most welcome, you can also visit <a href="http://www.bouhablog.com/">my blog</a> if you want to know me better.</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">By the way, the verdict from the Zurich HUB will be announced on Dec 20th (in a few hours), please wish me good luck :)</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">Amin</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Measuring AC mains energy use the non-invasive current transformer method - part 2]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2009/08/measuring-ac-mains-energy-use-non/"/>
    <updated>2009-08-05T13:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2009/08/measuring-ac-mains-energy-use-non</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last few weeks I have been working on measuring AC mains energy use using the non-invasive current transformer method. I’ve updated the website with a page about what I’ve done and how it works <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/28">here</a> (there’s still some work to be done on the page, but most of the info is there now).<br /><br /><a onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}" href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Yqa3j9ZhET8/SnmHOcRSRAI/AAAAAAAAAY4/c_G8bq4cDtg/s1600-h/noninv01s2.JPG"><img style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 400px; height: 194px;" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Yqa3j9ZhET8/SnmHOcRSRAI/AAAAAAAAAY4/c_G8bq4cDtg/s400/noninv01s2.JPG" alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5366469113165267970" border="0" /></a><span style="font-style: italic;">Measuring energy use in a power strip above- but is just as easy to measure whole house electrical energy use by cliping the sensor to the mains input to the house. </span></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Software improvement and examples]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2009/06/software-improvement-and-examples/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-25T22:02:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2009/06/software-improvement-and-examples</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have made a start on rewriting parts of the software to make the code a bit more object orientated and easier to use. I was finding that every time I needed to adapt the software for a different use it was a bit messy.<br /><br />In the process of doing a the re-write I will be adding examples of each significant part of the whole program working independently.<br /><br />Have a look on the <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/3">software page</a> for part 01 - Reading data from the Arduino and conversion of the data to a useful form.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
