<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sustainability | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/sustainability/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-27T09:13:37+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Part 3: Aggregated supply and demand across multiple households]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/05/Part3-Aggregated-supply-and-demand/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-02T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/05/Part3-Aggregated-supply-and-demand</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the main problems with looking at demand at the single household level is that demand at this level is very spiky, there are often long periods of low use around 100W and then suddenly a kettle or electric car charger turns on and demand increases by 20-30x in an instant. Solar generation can be very spiky too and so there is room for matching but it can be difficult to get the timing right.</p>

<p>One solution to increasing supply &amp; demand matching at the household level is to have in home battery storage and diversion to hot water stores – but it may not be the best solution for all cases.</p>

<p>Aggregating supply and demand across households provides an example of how the degree of matching can be increased significantly by what could be described as sequential demand. Not everyone boils a kettle at the same time or a cloud passing over one households solar pv system may not be passing over another’s.</p>

<p>In order to explore the extent of increased matching possible through aggregation of supply and demand I have been working with Dominic McCann from Carbon Coop on what could be called a <a href="https://openenergymonitor.org/dev/smartgrid"><strong>‘virtual microgrid’ concept</strong></a>, we have a provisional front page for this here - please note that its still in early development:</p>

<p><img src="/images/smart-grid.png" alt="image" /></p>

<!--more-->

<p>With only four households aggregating on-site solar, off-site wind, hydro and consumption and with total supply matching total demand over the whole period achieved by scaling the wind component, we can see matching increasing from 46% in the previous example to around 64% here. The resulting average carbon intensity is 132gCO2/kWh.</p>

<p>At this carbon intensity a heatpump (@ COP 3.0) has a delivered heat carbon intensity of 44gCO2/kWh, 81% less than gas and an EV (@ 3.7 miles/kWh) has a carbon intensity of 22gCO2/km 80% less than a very efficient petrol car doing 60 real world mpg, this compares with a carbon saving of roughly 45% vs direct gas heating and a petrol car if the electricity supply was from a grid supply consisting of gas, coal and nuclear at present UK proportions. Its a bit more complicated than this as more of the co2 was emitted when the EV was charging than at other times, the overall carbon intensity is just an average, Il come back to a more in-depth analysis of this again.</p>

<p>The result goes some way to illustrating why a mixture of renewable generation sources and aggregated demand ultimately increases the usefulness of the renewable supply and reflects the kind of results we see from running hourly zero carbon energy system models such as the one developed by the Center for Alternative Technology. These indicate that matching levels of between 62% and 78% are possible before storage and significant demand shifting with normal electric demand, heatpump heating demand and EV charging demand. See <a href="(https://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel/)">modelled supply/demand matching</a> based on ZeroCarbonBritain data:</p>

<p><a href="https://openenergymonitor.org/dev/smartgrid">Smart grid test intro page</a></p>

<p>Visible currently on the community smart grid test front page is the participating households renewable supply mix, real-time information on grid CO2 intensity and grid wind, solar and hydro. Household demand is not currently shown as there are not enough participants for the demand profile to be sufficiently anonymous.</p>

<p><img src="/images/supply.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>At the top of the page is a UK grid status indicator that is based on Dominic McCann’s work explained in more detail in <a href="http://carbon.coop/blog/zapaman/community-smart-grid-prosumer-perspective-part-2">Dominic’s blog post</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/smartgrid2.png" alt="image" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Part 2: Exploring carbon intensity and renewable energy matching]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/04/Part2-Exploring-carbon-intensity/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-28T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/04/Part2-Exploring-carbon-intensity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/winderful.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>This post describes an approach we have been exploring that uses the MyEnergy emoncms app and work on virtual <a href="https://github.com/TrystanLea/VirtualSmartGrid">smart grids</a> with Dominic McCann from Carbon Coop. There’s a good blog and video on what we’ve been working on over on the <a href="http://carbon.coop/blog/jonathan/smart-grid-aggregation-dashboard-prototype">Carbon Coop blog</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="/2016/04/Understand-CO2-intensity-grid-electricity/">last post</a> described two approaches to grid carbon intensity that consider the UK grid as a whole. This approach explores what the overall household carbon intensity might be when on-site renewable energy is considered such as home solar but also when renewable energy is bought over the grid, this could be from a green electricity tariff.</p>

<p>If imported electricity is supplied from a 100% renewable energy supplier in the UK: a large portion of the supply will likely be wind energy (54% of good energy’s ‘fuel’ mix comes from wind) and the UK has the best wind resource in Europe. Incorporating grid wind data and exploring matching with wind and solar, means we can really start to test scenarios such as ZeroCarbonBritain in the present.</p>

<p>There is real-time data available on UK wind supply and its possible to scale the total UK wind output in order to estimate a household ‘share of UK wind’ in real-time.</p>

<!--more-->

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>Calculating a households share of real-time wind output

Between March 2015 and March 2016 the output of UK wind power was on average 2630MW.

If a household buys 54% of 3300 kWh (typical annual household electricity consumption) or about 1800 kWh this converts to an average power of 205 Watts.

The scaling factor to convert total wind power output in MW to a household share is therefore:

scaling factor = 205 W / 2630 MW

The wind power available at any given moment would then be

wind power available = ( 205W / 2630MW ) x uk wind power output (MW)

If total UK wind power is 4000MW the estimated amount available in this example for the household is = (205W/2630MW) x 4000MW = 312 Watts.

Over the year the average available wind power for the household will work out to being 205W but for any given moment it could be more or less than this depending on how much power is being generated at that moment.
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>With data on household demand, onsite solar and a share of UK wind, we then work out how much backup supply is needed and from this an estimate of household CO2 intensity.</p>

<p>The backup CO2 intensity could be a single source such as CCGT gas power or a grid CO2 intensity with the wind power component removed in order to avoid double counting. Using an intensity based on grid: coal, gas, nuclear and interconnectors with the wind component removed may help incentivise use outside of peak periods but as discussed in the last post an extended analysis would be needed to establish what’s best from a carbon perspective.</p>

<p><img src="/images/week6.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p><em>Above: Emoncms MyEnergy App showing onsite solar (yellow), share of uk wind estimate (green) and household demand (blue). Available on emoncms.org or self-hosted installations.</em></p>

<p>The average CO2 intensities that result from this approach depend on the degree of matching between household demand and the renewable supply. From our experience so far matching can be anywhere between 40% and 70% depending on the nature of the household demand and how much demand shifting effort is undertaken. The resulting average carbon intensity is directly proportional to the level of matching: 40% matching means we need backup supply to cover 60% of the demand reducing the carbon intensity by 40% compared to grid average or perhaps CCGT gas CO2 intensity.</p>

<p>While far from perfect as no account is taken of what is actually happening on the local network, this approach could be seen as a good middle ground between on the one hand saying that all grid electricity has to be counted at grid average carbon intensity and on the other that all electricity from a green tariff is zero carbon at all times. It provides an incentive for demand shifting to times of high renewable output, while reflecting a substantial carbon reduction benefit that should be available from buying renewable energy across the grid.</p>

<h3 id="excessexported-renewable-energy">Excess/exported renewable energy</h3>
<p>There is an interesting question as to what happens to excess renewable energy not used by the household in this approach. If the energy is exported to the grid and used by others effectively displacing otherwise needed fossil fuel generation then this carbon saving could offset the carbon emissions emitted by the household when backup electricity was used. The result could mean that regardless of the degree of matching achieved between renewable supply and demand, whether on-site solar or wider grid renewable, the household could achieve net zero carbon by generating and equal amount of renewable supply as demand over a longer time period such as a year. This is a commonly used argument for net zero buildings. On the one hand it makes sense but on the other it relies on there being a wider fossil fuel powered grid in order to displace the fossil fuel generation and it substantially removes the incentive for renewable supply/demand matching.</p>

<h3 id="displaced-carbon">Displaced carbon</h3>
<p>Perhaps a better way to look at the displaced carbon issue is who is it that actually gets to claim the zero carbon benefit of that electricity. It would make sense that exported electricity is sold and then bought by the other party, once you’re buying renewable energy you would expect to be able to claim the zero carbon benefit of that energy as the user. Counting the exported electricity if bought by another user as displaced carbon would result in double counting in this case.</p>

<p>This is somewhat complicated by fact that exported solar pv electricity is not metered for small domestic installations in the UK. Instead the amount exported is assumed to be 50% of total generation. The exported electricity is paid for at around 4.91p/kWh but not measured. It’s not clear who gets to claim the carbon saved.</p>

<h3 id="next-aggregation">Next: Aggregation</h3>
<p>The degree of matching can be increased by aggregating supply and demand across several households. Not everyone boils a kettle at the same time or a cloud passing over one households solar pv system may not be passing over another’s. We have been testing with a limited number of households so far, the effect of aggregation on the degree of supply/demand matching which I will come on to in the next post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Part 1: Attempting to measure and understand the CO2 intensity of grid electricity]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/04/Understand-CO2-intensity-grid-electricity/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-27T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/04/Understand-CO2-intensity-grid-electricity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Zero carbon energy scenarios such as <a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/">ZeroCarbonBritain</a> feature significant electrification of energy demands previously provided by fossil fuels such as heating and transport. With electrification it becomes possible to supply these energy demands with renewably generated electricity from primarily wind, solar and backed up by storage technologies from short term stores such as batteries to long term stores such as power to gas.</p>

<p>We do not of course yet have a zero carbon grid. However there has been significant growth of renewable energy and a decline in coal generation in recent years.</p>

<p>The CO2 emissions of demand side solutions such as heat pumps and electric vehicles are significantly affected by the co2 intensity of the supply but in many cases installing and using these technologies make sense at the UK’s present supply mix and can make more or less sense depending on how you calculate co2 intensity and where you assume the additional electricity required comes from.</p>

<!--more-->

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>As an example the CO2 intensity of combined cycle gas turbines (CCGT) which provide the majority of electricity generated from gas in the UK have a co2 intensity of 360gCO2/kWh.

At this intensity a well installed heat pump that achieves an average COP of 3.0 delivers heat at a CO2 intensity of 129gCO2/kWh heat including 7% grid losses. This provides a significant 44% co2 emissions reduction compared to having an efficient gas boiler which delivers heat at a CO2 intensity of 230gCO2/kWh.

An electric car achieving a real world mountainous north Wales terrain driving efficiency of 3.7 miles per kWh (5.9km/kWh) including charging losses powered by gas electricity has a co2 intensity of 61gCO2/kWh which again provides a significant 44% co2 emissions reduction compared to real world efficient small petrol car co2 emissions of110 gCO2/km based on: 10.6 kgCO2 per gallon [1] and 60mpg (typical of the most efficient small car real world mpg [2].
</code></pre>
</div>
<p><a href="http://www.carbonindependent.org/sources_car.html">[1]</a>
<a href="http://www.whatcar.com/car-news/real-world-mpg-efficient-small-cars/1214063">[2]</a></p>

<p>The average CO2 intensity for the UK grid as a whole in 2015 was <a href="http://www.earth.org.uk/note-on-UK-grid-CO2-intensity-variations.html">367gCO2/kWh</a> http://www.earth.org.uk/note-on-UK-grid-CO2-intensity-variations.html#fullyear2015 - providing similar CO2 emission reduction potential to the gas only calculations above.</p>

<p>It is interesting to note that this average, results from coal generation with a CO2 intensity of 910gCO2/kWh being offset somewhat by generation from renewable energy and nuclear at 0gCO2/kWh resulting in a CO2 intensity that is close to what it would be if gas CCGT was our only supply source – which really highlights how carbon intensive coal is.</p>

<p>When we move energy demands from one form to another such as replacing a gas boiler with a heat pump the carbon reduction benefits depend heavily on what kind of generation provides for that additional demand. If the additional demand is provided for by CCGT gas turbines the switch makes sense, if it is provided by coal generation at 910gCO2/kWh it does not make so much sense. If it is provided by mix of renewable energy and CCGT is will make even more sense.</p>

<p>There are several different approaches to calculating the co2 intensity of delivered electricity each with their benefits and drawbacks which I will try and explore below and in further posts.</p>

<p>Whole grid averageHere we consider the grid as one big system with the CO2 intensity calculated as the total CO2 emitted by all forms of generation divided by the total demand over an extended period of time – one or more years. The co2 intensity of the UK electricity grid for 2015 was 367gCO2/kWh.</p>

<p>Near real-time co2 intensity using grid wide data</p>

<p>Here the CO2 intensity is calculated by the total CO2 emitted divided by total demand on typically a 10 minute basis. The CO2 intensity calculated this way will often show higher CO2 intensity in the day where gas and coal are a larger percentage of overall supply than at night time. CO2 intensity is also higher when its colder where demand is pushed up by higher heating requirements.</p>

<p><img src="/images/ukgrid.png" alt="UK Grid Carbon" /></p>

<p><a href="https://openenergymonitor.org/ukgrid">OpenEnergyMonitor UK Grid page</a> showing real-time CO2 Intensity.</p>

<p>If we use this real-time CO2 intensity in order to choose when to use electricity it gets more complicated, we may decide to shift electric vehicle charging or heat pump hot water heating to the night time in order to make use of grid carbon intensities that can often be 50-100gCO2/kWh less than day-time rates, but is this really a valid approach? The lower CO2 intensities at night are as a result of demand being lower and nuclear + renewables making up a larger share of generation, if night time demand is increased through demand shifting, turning on more gas and coal power plants, the carbon intensity would increase as well.</p>

<p>Given that most of the dis-patchable generation is gas and coal and assuming low levels of wind curtailment at night then it could be argued that the effective carbon intensity of moving demand to the night time should be calculated at the carbon intensity of this dis-patchable generation which depends on the proportion of gas to coal, a more in depth understanding as to how the proportion of gas and coal generation is decided would be needed to assess the carbon value of demand shifting. If the proportions are constant, shifting would make no difference, if gas is ramped up to meet the additional demand there may well be a benefit to shifting on the other hand if the difference is made up with more coal generation there would not be. There’s a bit more on this here using 2011 data from <a href="http://people.bath.ac.uk/en8sc/GridCarbonIntensity.pdf">Sam Cooper of Bath University</a> <a href="http://www.earth.org.uk/note-on-UK-grid-CO2-intensity-variations.html">linked from earth notes here</a>.</p>

<p>Shifting demand away from peak times may well make sense from a transmission and distribution grid capacity perspective but this is largely a different argument and would require a different calculation to assess. It may also be the case that some wind curtailment does take place although the precise extent of this and where on the grid using more will reduce curtailment is difficult to quantify.</p>

<p>In the next blog I will discuss the work I’ve been doing with Dominic McCann from the Carbon Coop on estimating CO2 intensity with onsite and green tariff renewable energy considered.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Source Circular Economy OSCEdays - emonPi Embodied Energy ]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/07/open-source-circular-economy-oscedays/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-05T19:48:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/07/open-source-circular-economy-oscedays</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-P6V6jHZByMA/VZmH3t6iH8I/AAAAAAAATa8/Ji4-lP05LZk/s1600/oscedays.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="230" src="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-P6V6jHZByMA/VZmH3t6iH8I/AAAAAAAATa8/Ji4-lP05LZk/s640/oscedays.png" width="640" /></a></div>
<p><br />Three weeks ago, time runs fast! I attended the open source circular economy event OSCEdays in London. It was a fantastic event with a lot of energy and ideas exploring how  the circular economy could benefit from an open source approach.<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-_Gn7kS9kGMQ/VZl965UyCJI/AAAAAAAATak/UMpLQ-RQ6-E/s1600/oscedays.jpeg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="260" src="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-_Gn7kS9kGMQ/VZl965UyCJI/AAAAAAAATak/UMpLQ-RQ6-E/s400/oscedays.jpeg" width="400" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;OSCEdays at FabLab London&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-iVHrLVdqWpY/VZl_FM3RFkI/AAAAAAAATas/FpO29-jdQSo/s1600/bda5d194978a0361.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="180" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-iVHrLVdqWpY/VZl_FM3RFkI/AAAAAAAATas/FpO29-jdQSo/s400/bda5d194978a0361.png" width="400" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2015/06/investigating-embodied-energy-of-emonpi.html">Initial draft embodied energy analysis of the emonpi</a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;There was a wide range of challenges and projects there including: circular makerspaces submitted by <a href="http://www.greatrecovery.org.uk/">the great recovery</a> looking at how fablab’s and makerspaces could encourage circular thinking, an initiative developing re-usable containers for cosmetics, a challenge looking at the implications of the circular economy for wearable technologies, ‘trust is not waste’ by <a href="http://www.therubbishdiet.org.uk/">the rubbish diet project</a> and ours looking at the embodied energy and lifecycle analysis of the OpenEnergyMonitor EmonPi.<br /><br />Id like to thank Rachel Stanley, David Green, WoonTan and Paidi Creed for all their help and input and for Erica Purvis and Sharon Prendeville for organising the event and the wider team that where involved in running the event in many other cities around the world.<br /><br />Our discussions and findings are partly documented here, there’s also a bit more that needs writing up which will be online soon: <a href="http://community.oscedays.org/t/headline-challenge-open-energy-life-cycles/662/2">http://community.oscedays.org/t/headline-challenge-open-energy-life-cycles/662/2</a>.<br /><br />The research that I did on the embodied energy of the emonpi in the lead up to the event can be found here: <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2015/06/investigating-embodied-energy-of-emonpi.html">http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2015/06/investigating-embodied-energy-of-emonpi.html</a><i> </i><br /><br />We are really interested in the lifecycle impacts and embodied energy side of OpenEnergyMonitor and so were going to keep building on this. I’ve almost finished a post that looks at the embodied energy calculation for the emonpi microcontroller and raspberrypi chips in more detail which will be up soon.<br /><br />If your interested in embodied energy, lifecycle impacts, the circular economy and how open source could play a part do check out OSCEdays <a href="https://oscedays.org/">https://oscedays.org</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Investigating the embodied energy of the EmonPi & OSCEDays London 12-14th June.]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/06/investigating-embodied-energy-of-emonpi/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-01T17:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/06/investigating-embodied-energy-of-emonpi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On the 12th – 14th of June there is an event happening called Open Source Circular Economy Days in many cities around the world, including in London <a href="https://oscedays.org/london/">https://oscedays.org/london/ </a>which we will be attending. I first found out about the event from Lars Zimmerman who is on the core organising team and I met last year at OuiShare, Lars runs <a href="http://openitagency.eu/">http://openitagency.eu</a> encouraging and helping people incorporate open source in their businesses, organisations and projects. The aim of Open Source Circular Economy Days is to bring open source thinking to the circular economy. The energy associated with manufacturing is a large part of our overall energy consumption and the question of embodied energy especially in the zero carbon energy sector is particularly important to understand better. There is quite a bit of discussion at the moment about the level of energy return on energy invested EROI required from the zero carbon energy sector as a whole in order to sustain a certain level of technological society.<br /><br />My impression of trying to look into embodied energy and life cycle analysis is that it seems that the measurement of embodied energy and other impacts associated with manufacturing our stuff and then the understanding of what solutions are available to reduce this embodied energy, especially in electronics is still in its infancy compared with other energy demands that we are more familiar with like the solutions available for space heating and transport, both of which have solutions that can achieve 70-90% energy reductions without reducing the level of comfort or distance travelled <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/sustainable-energy.">http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/sustainable-energy.</a><br /><br />We’re particular conscious of this question at OpenEnergyMonitor as we get our hardware manufactured and see the quantity of stuff involved in the production of our equipment. It has always been interesting to read about developments from other projects and companies who have been looking at this for sometime but in different fields predominantly outdoor clothing: <a href="http://www.patagonia.com/us/footprint">http://www.patagonia.com/us/footprint</a> and <a href="http://www.howies.co.uk/">http://www.howies.co.uk</a>. They have often achieved quite substantial improvements by looking at their materials, and supply chains in detail.<br /><br />With Open Source Circular Economy Days coming up and after talking to Erica Purvis of <a href="http://technicalnature.org.uk/">http://technicalnature.org.uk/</a> who is one of the organisers of the London even we decided to try and sketch out a draft initial analysis of the embodied energy associated with the emonpi to take along with us. I emphasised its initial status there because I don’t have a high confidence in the reliability  of the data at the moment but I think it does provide a useful start on which further detailed research can be done.<br /><br /><b>Embodied Energy Audit Process</b><br /><br />With a little research I found an example of an embodied energy analysis for an LED light with an accompanying dataset for the embodied energy of different components here: <a href="http://users.humboldt.edu/arne/Alstone_etal_Lumina-TR9-Embodied-Energy_Jan11.pdf">http://users.humboldt.edu/arne/Alstone_etal_Lumina-TR9-Embodied-Energy_Jan11.pdf</a> this example referenced data from the European commission project  Eco-design of energy-using products: <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/policies/sustainable-business/ecodesign/methodology/files/eup_ecoreport_v5_en.xls.">http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/policies/sustainable-business/ecodesign/methodology/files/eup_ecoreport_v5_en.xls.</a><br /><br />I then calculated an estimate for embodied energy by using the embodied energy dataset from these two sources and a detailed list of components for the emonpi including the weight of each component. The spreadsheet with the calculation can be downloaded here on the EmonPI open hardware github repository:<br /><br /><a href="https://github.com/openenergymonitor/Hardware/raw/master/emonPi/emonPi_V1_5/emonpi_embodiedenergy.ods">https://github.com/openenergymonitor/Hardware/raw/master/emonPi/emonPi_V1_5/emonpi_embodiedenergy.ods </a><br /><br />here’s a screenshot of what it looks like:<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-lABYn1a7cMM/VWyZvr5dIKI/AAAAAAAAR8k/d_QjLgYKRXk/s1600/emodiedenergycalc.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="284" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-lABYn1a7cMM/VWyZvr5dIKI/AAAAAAAAR8k/d_QjLgYKRXk/s640/emodiedenergycalc.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><br />I have summarised the main results in these two graphics:<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-WhIT__7XvzI/VWyZordmN9I/AAAAAAAAR8c/8-9FteeWTz8/s1600/emonpiembodiedenergy01.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="289" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-WhIT__7XvzI/VWyZordmN9I/AAAAAAAAR8c/8-9FteeWTz8/s640/emonpiembodiedenergy01.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;Interestingly the application of the embodied energy values in the dataset suggest that at least for the parts that we are most involved in the custom design of (The EmonPi Shield and the aluminium enclosure) the embodied energy is dominated first by the enclosure at 10.1 kWh and then by the manufacturing of the printed circuit board (2.2 kWh) and the assembly of the unit (1.6 kWh). The integrated circuits only account for a relatively small percentage at 0.2 kWh.<br /><br /><b>Aluminium enclosures</b><br />The estimate for the embodied energy of the aluminium enclosure is based on the 40 kWh/kg figure in Sustainable Energy without the hot air. This equates to 144 MJ/kg which is lower than a couple of other figures I could find for standard aluminium embodied energy. The Wikipedia figure is 155MJ/kg and is based on a 33% recycling rate. The figures I could find for the embodied energy for aluminium from bauxite where between 191MJ/kg and 342MJ/kg. The enclosure made from aluminium from bauxite could at the higher end use 24 kWh and at the lower end require 16 kWh. 100% Recycled aluminium however only requires between 11.35MJ/kg and 17MJ/kg. The EmonPi manufactured from 100% recycled aluminium would therefore only need between 0.9 - 1.3 kWh to manufacture. The EmonTH ABS plastic case is about a third of the size of the EmonPI case and weighs 32g it had an embodied energy of around 1.0 kWh (111MJ/kg). A plastic EmonPi case might weight about 3x this (~90 grams) and so may use around 3.0 kWh. The aluminium would need have been recycled around 7-8 times to achieve the same level of embodied energy as an ABS plastic enclosure. There are also lower embodied energy plastics available such as Polypropylene (64-94MJ/kg) and recycled PET  may use around 42-55MJ/kg and then perhaps there are even more options in the design of enclosures to minimise the amount of material used.<br /><b><br />Manufacture of printed circuit boards and assembly</b><br />Beyond learning more about enclosure options it would be useful to focus on getting a better idea for the reliability of the data for printed circuit board manufacturing and assembly and what options exist to lower their embodied energy requirements.<br /><br /><b>OSCEDays</b><br />If your interested in learning more about the Open Source Circular Economy days event or joining us at the event in London have a look at the event pages here:<br /><a href="https://oscedays.org/">https://oscedays.org</a><br /><a href="https://oscedays.org/london">https://oscedays.org/london</a><br /><b><br />Useful links and references:</b><br />&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://users.humboldt.edu/arne/Alstone_etal_Lumina-TR9-Embodied-Energy_Jan11.pdf">http://users.humboldt.edu/arne/Alstone_etal_Lumina-TR9-Embodied-Energy_Jan11.pdf</a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/policies/sustainable-business/ecodesign/methodology/files/eup_ecoreport_v5_en.xls.">http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/policies/sustainable-business/ecodesign/methodology/files/eup_ecoreport_v5_en.xls.</a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://energy-solution.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/What-We-Know-and-Don---t-Know-about-Embodied-Energy-and-Greenhouse_Energy-Solutions_ACEEE-2012.pdf">http://energy-solution.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/What-We-Know-and-Don—t-Know-about-Embodied-Energy-and-Greenhouse_Energy-Solutions_ACEEE-2012.pdf</a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://www.inference.phy.cam.ac.uk/withouthotair/c15/page_88.shtml">http://www.inference.phy.cam.ac.uk/withouthotair/c15/page_88.shtml</a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://www.appropedia.org/Life_cycle_analysis_of_polymer_recycling_literature_review">http://www.appropedia.org/Life_cycle_analysis_of_polymer_recycling_literature_review</a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2013/08/ethical-and-sustainable-electronics.html">http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2013/08/ethical-and-sustainable-electronics.html</a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2013/09/faire-maus.html">http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2013/09/faire-maus.html</a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2012/05/embodied-energy-of-electronic-enclosure.html">http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2012/05/embodied-energy-of-electronic-enclosure.html</a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
