<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sustainability | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/sustainability/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-30T15:36:24+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Attempting to measure and understand the CO2 intensity of grid electricity]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/04/Understand-CO2-intensity-grid-electricity/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-18T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2016/04/ Understand-CO2-intensity-grid-electricity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Zero carbon energy scenarios such as <a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/">ZeroCarbonBritain</a> feature significant electrification of energy demands previously provided by fossil fuels such as heating and transport. With electrification it becomes possible to supply these energy demands with renewably generated electricity from primarily wind, solar and backed up by storage technologies from short term stores such as batteries to long term stores such as power to gas.</p>

<p>We do not of course yet have a zero carbon grid. However there has been significant growth of renewable energy and a decline in coal generation in recent years.</p>

<p>The CO2 emissions of demand side solutions such as heat pumps and electric vehicles are significantly affected by the co2 intensity of the supply but in many cases installing and using these technologies make sense at the UK’s present supply mix and can make more or less sense depending on how you calculate co2 intensity and where you assume the additional electricity required comes from.</p>

<!--more-->

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>As an example the CO2 intensity of combined cycle gas turbines (CCGT) which provide the majority of electricity generated from gas in the UK have a co2 intensity of 360gCO2/kWh.

At this intensity a well installed heat pump that achieves an average COP of 3.0 delivers heat at a CO2 intensity of 129gCO2/kWh heat including 7% grid losses. This provides a significant 44% co2 emissions reduction compared to having an efficient gas boiler which delivers heat at a CO2 intensity of 230gCO2/kWh.

An electric car achieving a real world mountainous north Wales terrain driving efficiency of 3.7 miles per kWh (5.9km/kWh) including charging losses powered by gas electricity has a co2 intensity of 61gCO2/kWh which again provides a significant 44% co2 emissions reduction compared to real world efficient small petrol car co2 emissions of110 gCO2/km based on: 10.6 kgCO2 per gallon [1] and 60mpg (typical of the most efficient small car real world mpg [2].
</code></pre>
</div>
<p><a href="http://www.carbonindependent.org/sources_car.html">[1]</a>
<a href="http://www.whatcar.com/car-news/real-world-mpg-efficient-small-cars/1214063">[2]</a></p>

<p>The average CO2 intensity for the UK grid as a whole in 2015 was <a href="http://www.earth.org.uk/note-on-UK-grid-CO2-intensity-variations.html#fullyear2015">367gCO2/kWh</a> http://www.earth.org.uk/note-on-UK-grid-CO2-intensity-variations.html#fullyear2015 - providing similar CO2 emission reduction potential to the gas only calculations above.</p>

<p>It is interesting to note that this average, results from coal generation with a CO2 intensity of 910gCO2/kWh being offset somewhat by generation from renewable energy and nuclear at 0gCO2/kWh resulting in a CO2 intensity that is close to what it would be if gas CCGT was our only supply source – which really highlights how carbon intensive coal is.</p>

<p>When we move energy demands from one form to another such as replacing a gas boiler with a heat pump the carbon reduction benefits depend heavily on what kind of generation provides for that additional demand. If the additional demand is provided for by CCGT gas turbines the switch makes sense, if it is provided by coal generation at 910gCO2/kWh it does not make so much sense. If it is provided by mix of renewable energy and CCGT is will make even more sense.</p>

<p>There are several different approaches to calculating the co2 intensity of delivered electricity each with their benefits and drawbacks which I will try and explore below and in further posts.</p>

<p>Whole grid averageHere we consider the grid as one big system with the CO2 intensity calculated as the total CO2 emitted by all forms of generation divided by the total demand over an extended period of time – one or more years. The co2 intensity of the UK electricity grid for 2015 was 367gCO2/kWh.</p>

<p>Near real-time co2 intensity using grid wide data</p>

<p>Here the CO2 intensity is calculated by the total CO2 emitted divided by total demand on typically a 10 minute basis. The CO2 intensity calculated this way will often show higher CO2 intensity in the day where gas and coal are a larger percentage of overall supply than at night time. CO2 intensity is also higher when its colder where demand is pushed up by higher heating requirements.</p>

<p><img src="/images/ukgrid.png" alt="UK Grid Carbon" /></p>

<p><a href="https://openenergymonitor.org/ukgrid">OpenEnergyMonitor UK Grid page</a> showing real-time CO2 Intensity.</p>

<p>If we use this real-time CO2 intensity in order to choose when to use electricity it gets more complicated, we may decide to shift electric vehicle charging or heat pump hot water heating to the night time in order to make use of grid carbon intensities that can often be 50-100gCO2/kWh less than day-time rates, but is this really a valid approach? The lower CO2 intensities at night are as a result of demand being lower and nuclear + renewables making up a larger share of generation, if night time demand is increased through demand shifting, turning on more gas and coal power plants, the carbon intensity would increase as well.</p>

<p>Given that most of the dis-patchable generation is gas and coal and assuming low levels of wind curtailment at night then it could be argued that the effective carbon intensity of moving demand to the night time should be calculated at the carbon intensity of this dis-patchable generation which depends on the proportion of gas to coal, a more in depth understanding as to how the proportion of gas and coal generation is decided would be needed to assess the carbon value of demand shifting. If the proportions are constant, shifting would make no difference, if gas is ramped up to meet the additional demand there may well be a benefit to shifting on the other hand if the difference is made up with more coal generation there would not be. There’s a bit more on this here using 2011 data from <a href="http://people.bath.ac.uk/en8sc/GridCarbonIntensity.pdf">Sam Cooper of Bath University</a> <a href="http://www.earth.org.uk/note-on-UK-grid-CO2-intensity-variations.html">linked from earth notes here</a>.</p>

<p>Shifting demand away from peak times may well make sense from a transmission and distribution grid capacity perspective but this is largely a different argument and would require a different calculation to assess. It may also be the case that some wind curtailment does take place although the precise extent of this and where on the grid using more will reduce curtailment is difficult to quantify.</p>

<p>In the next blog I will discuss the work I’ve been doing with Dominic McCann from the Carbon Coop on estimating CO2 intensity with onsite and green tariff renewable energy considered.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An open source hourly zero carbon energy system model]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/02/an-open-source-hourly-zero-carbon/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-06T01:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/02/an-open-source-hourly-zero-carbon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been doing some work recently with Philip James from the Centre for Alternative Technology  on developing a set of open source zero carbon energy system models  based on <a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/">ZeroCarbonBritain</a> that visualise in a javascript based web page application how energy demand  can be supplied by a variable renewable energy supply using a mix of  storage technologies. You can create your own scenarios, choosing how  much wind, solar, storage technologies etc are used.<br /><br />Its still work in progress but the models we have built<span class="text_exposed_show"> so far are now online and can be explored here:<br /> <a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/energy_model/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">http://zerocarbonbritain.org/energy_model</a></span><br /><br />The source code is all available there too as well as the original ZeroCarbonBritain spreadsheet model: <a href="https://github.com/philJam/energymodel">https://github.com/philJam/energymodel</a><br /><br />Visualising hourly surplus and shortfall:<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-GvNCSRnIum0/VNQO64pJuYI/AAAAAAAAOWU/FwIXxOjYfxE/s1600/screenshot.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-GvNCSRnIum0/VNQO64pJuYI/AAAAAAAAOWU/FwIXxOjYfxE/s1600/screenshot.png" height="336" width="400" /> </a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;Visualising battery, hydrogen, synthetic liquid and gas store levels:&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-GpTxQG9x5ps/VNQO8Vc2BWI/AAAAAAAAOWc/uHHiIVeKVgk/s1600/store.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-GpTxQG9x5ps/VNQO8Vc2BWI/AAAAAAAAOWc/uHHiIVeKVgk/s1600/store.png" height="321" width="400" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />This builds partly on findings and questions raised from our earlier work on the Snowdonia household energy study: here;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2014/11/snowdonia-household-energy-study.html">http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2014/11/snowdonia-household-energy-study.html</a><br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-knYU11AkW_A/VNQPjbpKzLI/AAAAAAAAOWk/OFmPN42NIU8/s1600/0present.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-knYU11AkW_A/VNQPjbpKzLI/AAAAAAAAOWk/OFmPN42NIU8/s1600/0present.png" height="176" width="400" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />The aim will be to extend that analysis to look at the amount of  renewable energy and energy storage required to supply the energy demand  after implementing measures like building insulation/retrofit,  heatpumps and electric transport.<br /><br /><br />I find it very interesting looking at how all of these  different elements can come together to create a zero carbon energy  system, to understand better the relevance of different solutions. With a  framework like this it becomes more possible to put ideas like smart  electric car charging or excess pv diversion to immersion heaters and  battery stores in context, to get a better idea of actually how much  effect different solutions can have.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kettle vs Blanket]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/12/kettle-vs-blanket/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-08T11:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/12/kettle-vs-blanket</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the things I love about monitoring energy is that it can be used to answer questions and inform decisions.<br />&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;In my household we have recently purchased an electric blanket, I had always associated such items as an indulgent luxury! However at this time of year the temperature in our bedroom is often only just about in double figures (old property with poor heating and frugal use) necessitating a seemingly moderate luxury of a hot water bottle to warm the bed up a little.   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I assumed using the new electric blanket would result in an increase in our power consumption, however the energy monitor proved me wrong! &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Having the electric blanket on for 30min used about 0.1KWh while boiling 1L of hot water to fill at hot water bottle used about 0.16KWh of energy, 60% more! Also the electric blanket does a much better job of warming the bed then the hot water bottle, after 30min it was almost uncomfortably hot even with an ambient temperature in the room of 11 degrees! &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<br /><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-PRWQK4f8cpM/VIFxhBOblbI/AAAAAAABAjg/B0fmE75iFEs/s1600/blanket.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-PRWQK4f8cpM/VIFxhBOblbI/AAAAAAABAjg/B0fmE75iFEs/s1600/blanket.png" height="456" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;200W Electric Blanket on for about 30 min&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-9WhNqhDkTyk/VIWOeVUmd6I/AAAAAAABAro/XBAaAxspyKg/s1600/Screenshot%2B2014-12-08%2Bat%2B11.38.19.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-9WhNqhDkTyk/VIWOeVUmd6I/AAAAAAABAro/XBAaAxspyKg/s1600/Screenshot%2B2014-12-08%2Bat%2B11.38.19.png" height="286" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Kettle heating 1L of water to boiling&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Snowdonia household energy study, exploring zero carbon solutions]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/11/snowdonia-household-energy-study/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T12:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/11/snowdonia-household-energy-study</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of years ago Glyn and I and a friend of ours Bethan Gritten carried out an energy study with a local organisation called EcoBro of 17 households in Snowdonia, North Wales including our own.<br /><br />We looked at the energy used by each household for electric, heating and transport and what the effect would be of applying the solutions outlined in both <a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/">ZeroCarbonBritain</a> and <a href="http://www.withouthotair.com/">Sustainable energy without the hot air</a>, visualising the result using David MacKay’s energy stack graphics.<br /><br />I’ve been looking again at this work recently as I find it a really useful  and tangible way of looking at the energy problem and I’ve taken the opportunity to improve the energy stack graphic visualisation and put it up online here:<br /><br /><b>Dynamic visualisation: </b><br /><a href="http://egni.ecobro.org/data">http://egni.ecobro.org/data</a><br /><br />The code for it is open source and on github here:<br /><a href="https://github.com/TrystanLea/energystacks">https://github.com/TrystanLea/energystacks</a><br /><br />Here’s a brief run through of what you can see:<br /><br /><b>Current Energy Use</b><br />This first graphic shows each households current energy use and where that energy is used:<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-3My6GQ159Bo/VG5sgwDxuVI/AAAAAAAAMIw/q7vJ1EF6nvY/s1600/0present.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-3My6GQ159Bo/VG5sgwDxuVI/AAAAAAAAMIw/q7vJ1EF6nvY/s1600/0present.png" height="282" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />24% of the energy used by the households come from renewable sources, whether biomass or 100% green electricity tariffs. The wide range of total energy use per household is quite interesting, using the dynamic tool you can explore the contribution of occupancy and floor area. You can also look at C02 and energy cost per household.<br /><br /><b>Solutions for reaching 100% sustainable energy for household electric, heating and transport.</b><br /><br />In both the ZeroCarbonBritain report and David MacKay’s Sustainable  Energy without the hot air, building retrofit (insulation and  air-tightness), heatpumps and electric vehicles form the cornerstone’s of  both significantly reducing the amount of energy we need to provide the  same amount of comfort/utility and making it possible to power the  remaining energy demand from electricity generated by sustainable energy.<br /><br />The following graphics show’s what the effect would be if each household in the study applied these measures:<br /><br /><b>1) All households switch current electric consumption to a 100% Green Electricity tariff:</b><br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-HAjBniXZgCk/VG5sqcRnTTI/AAAAAAAAMI4/wUTAyUOrzEc/s1600/1greenelec.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-HAjBniXZgCk/VG5sqcRnTTI/AAAAAAAAMI4/wUTAyUOrzEc/s1600/1greenelec.png" height="283" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><b>2) 100% green electric powered heatpumps, Biomass and electric cooking instead of oil, gas and coal. </b>For heatpumps it assumes replacing existing heat input with a heatpump with a COP of 3.0. See step 5 for a very basic application of building performance retrofit work.<br /><br />Heatpumps form the cornerstone of supplying the remaining heat demand  after retrofit in both Zero Carbon Britain and David MacKay’s  sustainable energy without the hot air. The performance of a heatpump is highly dependent of course on being designed, installed and controlled correctly.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-cBsMQMzhm1M/VG5s1Wd8BqI/AAAAAAAAMJA/3BXvVWkJHUg/s1600/2heating.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-cBsMQMzhm1M/VG5s1Wd8BqI/AAAAAAAAMJA/3BXvVWkJHUg/s1600/2heating.png" height="282" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><b>3) Switch all petrol and diesel cars to electric cars powered by renewable electricity </b>(Assuming mileage stays constant and an electric car performance of 4.0 Miles/kWh)<br /><br />The ZeroCarbonBritain report from CAT suggests a reduction in the number  of miles driven through a combination of increased use of pubic  transport, walking, biking and better planning of where we live in  relation to work/activities in addition to a switch to electric vehicles  which are both more efficient than petrol and diesel cars and can be  powered by renewable electricity.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-lcZ0NG6-YWc/VG5tQICN2xI/AAAAAAAAMJI/LA2FrARb0CQ/s1600/3electriccars.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-lcZ0NG6-YWc/VG5tQICN2xI/AAAAAAAAMJI/LA2FrARb0CQ/s1600/3electriccars.png" height="283" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><b>4) Electric trains instead of planes:</b><br /><br />In order to achieve the last 15% and still enjoy travelling long  distances we would need a switch from flights to electric train  journey’s, the model here just assumes that the number of flight miles  are replaced with electric train miles powered by renewable electricity and that the destination is reachable by train.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-69_K4jfM7Ik/VG5vP_2zs7I/AAAAAAAAMJc/-5hyXVWq_eM/s1600/4electrictrains.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-69_K4jfM7Ik/VG5vP_2zs7I/AAAAAAAAMJc/-5hyXVWq_eM/s1600/4electrictrains.png" height="282" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><br /><b>5) At least 120 kWh/m2.year primary energy for space heating and home electric.</b><br /><br />Improving the thermal performance of buildings by adding insulation and  improving the air-tightness should be one of the first measures applied  and considered before or at the same time as any heating system changes as in step 2 above. The implementation of applying retrofit measures in the energy stack visualisation model here is only to set a maximum primary energy use requirement rather than to explore what’s possible on a house by house basis which would give a better picture of the potential savings from retrofit work.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-KCL_Q5nWXLE/VG5tb3QwaTI/AAAAAAAAMJQ/kPdsojZwA0w/s1600/5buildingefficiency.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-KCL_Q5nWXLE/VG5tb3QwaTI/AAAAAAAAMJQ/kPdsojZwA0w/s1600/5buildingefficiency.png" height="281" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><br /><b>Powering Up with Renewable Energy</b><br /><br />The ZeroCarbonBritain report goes into a lot of detail on how the remaining energy demand after applying power down measures can be supplied by renewable energy and also the need for storage technologies to manage the intermittent nature of a fully renewable energy supply. We didnt look into this as part of our study but it would be interesting to explore it in more detail in the future to answer questions such as: what scale of community energy projects such as community wind, solar and hydro should we be thinking of if we are to supply our energy demands after applying power down measures? and how much should we be thinking about energy storage in a more local context?<br /><br />There’s a lot of things that could be improved about the study.  Rather than applying back of the envelope calculations on the effects  of applying the various solutions to each house it would be better to look at each house in detail, carrying out a full detailed Carbon Coop home energy assessment for each house on how energy demand can be reduced by up to 70% through retrofit work.<br /><br /><b>Related links</b><br /><br />OpenEnergyMonitor page on Sustainable Energy:<br /><a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/sustainable-energy">http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/sustainable-energy</a><br /><br />The ZeroCarbonBritain report:<br /><a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/">http://zerocarbonbritain.org/</a><br /><a href="http://vimeo.com/album/2648454/video/81962195">Alice Hooker-Stroud, Centre for Alternative Technology, ‘Zero Carbon Britain (Energy)’</a> <br /><br />Sustainable energy without the hot air <br /><a href="http://withouthotair.com/">http://withouthotair.com/</a><br /><br />Carbon Coop<br /><a href="http://vimeo.com/album/2648454/video/81956917">Charlie Baker’s talk about carbon coop and 80% retrofit at the radical emissions reduction conference</a><br /><br /><br /><b>Where next?</b><br />I would be interested to hear any thoughts on how to develop this work further, where it should go next. Feel free to email me if you have any ideas or would like to discuss: trystanlea at openenergymonitor.org</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Faire Maus! A 'fair' USB optical mouse]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/09/faire-maus/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T15:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/09/faire-maus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago I wrote a <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2013/08/ethical-and-sustainable-electronics.html">blog post about ethical and sustainable electronics</a>.<br /><br />In the post I mentioned a German project called <a href="https://www.nager-it.de/en">Nager IT</a> who have designed an optical USB mouse using low carbon materials and have gone to great lengths to source ethically produced components with a transparent supply chain and exploitation free manufacture.<br /><br />We have decided to support the Nager IT project by becoming a UK reseller of their ‘Faire Maus’ or fair mouse. This mouse is as good as it gets at the moment in terms of ethical and sustainable electronics.<br /><br /><i>The mouse is a well-made three-button USB optical scroll wheel mouse made using low carbon materials, ethically produced components with a transparent supply chain and exploitation free manufacture.</i><br /><br />The mouse is now available for purchase on a non profit basis (for us) in our shop: <a href="http://shop.openenergymonitor.com/fair-usb-optical-mouse/">http://shop.openenergymonitor.com/fair-usb-optical-mouse/</a><br /><br />&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-7sdg6VzJAtE/UjckC6z5G9I/AAAAAAAAkMM/OE4NglI0Nkw/s1600/NagerIT+flyer1.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="452" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-7sdg6VzJAtE/UjckC6z5G9I/AAAAAAAAkMM/OE4NglI0Nkw/s640/NagerIT+flyer1.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-SGiD5PHvM0E/UjckC3mlDdI/AAAAAAAAkMQ/x2hp4S_ruUQ/s1600/NagerITflyer2.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="450" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-SGiD5PHvM0E/UjckC3mlDdI/AAAAAAAAkMQ/x2hp4S_ruUQ/s640/NagerITflyer2.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<em style="margin: 0px; outline: none; padding: 0px;"><strong style="margin: 0px; outline: none; padding: 0px;"><br /></strong></em>&lt;/div&gt;The mice are assembled by hand in Germany and feel very well made, the texture of the wood plastic enclosure feels good in the hand and the sleek and rubbery USB cable runs smoothy over the table.<br />&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-wsoOK0yG8U8/UjckqjNUlWI/AAAAAAAAkMc/geznhTZCmQU/s1600/2013_08_29_16.39.32__74936.1379344820.1280.1280.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="240" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-wsoOK0yG8U8/UjckqjNUlWI/AAAAAAAAkMc/geznhTZCmQU/s320/2013_08_29_16.39.32__74936.1379344820.1280.1280.jpg" width="320" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;<br />Every time I use the mouse it it reminds me that ethical and sustainable electronics is a goal which is worth pursuing.<br /><br /><i>Purchasing a fair mouse can be thought of like purchasing fair trade coffee; it might cost a little bit extra but you know that your doing good.</i><br />&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;Checkout the <a href="https://www.nager-it.de/static/pdf/en_lieferkette.pdf">great graphic</a> Nager IT have produced illustrating their transparent supply chain behind this mouse.<br />&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PMWAqYm35nk/UjclPvTHpdI/AAAAAAAAkMk/iogDpL-pMA8/s1600/2013-08-29+16.39.51.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="240" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PMWAqYm35nk/UjclPvTHpdI/AAAAAAAAkMk/iogDpL-pMA8/s320/2013-08-29+16.39.51.jpg" width="320" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;<br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
