<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sustainability | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/sustainability/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-22T01:38:15+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An open source hourly zero carbon energy system model]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/02/an-open-source-hourly-zero-carbon/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-06T01:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/02/an-open-source-hourly-zero-carbon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been doing some work recently with Philip James from the Centre for Alternative Technology  on developing a set of open source zero carbon energy system models  based on <a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/">ZeroCarbonBritain</a> that visualise in a javascript based web page application how energy demand  can be supplied by a variable renewable energy supply using a mix of  storage technologies. You can create your own scenarios, choosing how  much wind, solar, storage technologies etc are used.<br /><br />Its still work in progress but the models we have built<span class="text_exposed_show"> so far are now online and can be explored here:<br /> <a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/energy_model/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">http://zerocarbonbritain.org/energy_model</a></span><br /><br />The source code is all available there too as well as the original ZeroCarbonBritain spreadsheet model: <a href="https://github.com/philJam/energymodel">https://github.com/philJam/energymodel</a><br /><br />Visualising hourly surplus and shortfall:<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-GvNCSRnIum0/VNQO64pJuYI/AAAAAAAAOWU/FwIXxOjYfxE/s1600/screenshot.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-GvNCSRnIum0/VNQO64pJuYI/AAAAAAAAOWU/FwIXxOjYfxE/s1600/screenshot.png" height="336" width="400" /> </a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;Visualising battery, hydrogen, synthetic liquid and gas store levels:&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-GpTxQG9x5ps/VNQO8Vc2BWI/AAAAAAAAOWc/uHHiIVeKVgk/s1600/store.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-GpTxQG9x5ps/VNQO8Vc2BWI/AAAAAAAAOWc/uHHiIVeKVgk/s1600/store.png" height="321" width="400" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />This builds partly on findings and questions raised from our earlier work on the Snowdonia household energy study: here;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2014/11/snowdonia-household-energy-study.html">http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2014/11/snowdonia-household-energy-study.html</a><br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-knYU11AkW_A/VNQPjbpKzLI/AAAAAAAAOWk/OFmPN42NIU8/s1600/0present.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-knYU11AkW_A/VNQPjbpKzLI/AAAAAAAAOWk/OFmPN42NIU8/s1600/0present.png" height="176" width="400" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />The aim will be to extend that analysis to look at the amount of  renewable energy and energy storage required to supply the energy demand  after implementing measures like building insulation/retrofit,  heatpumps and electric transport.<br /><br /><br />I find it very interesting looking at how all of these  different elements can come together to create a zero carbon energy  system, to understand better the relevance of different solutions. With a  framework like this it becomes more possible to put ideas like smart  electric car charging or excess pv diversion to immersion heaters and  battery stores in context, to get a better idea of actually how much  effect different solutions can have.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kettle vs Blanket]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/12/kettle-vs-blanket/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-08T11:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/12/kettle-vs-blanket</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the things I love about monitoring energy is that it can be used to answer questions and inform decisions.<br />&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;In my household we have recently purchased an electric blanket, I had always associated such items as an indulgent luxury! However at this time of year the temperature in our bedroom is often only just about in double figures (old property with poor heating and frugal use) necessitating a seemingly moderate luxury of a hot water bottle to warm the bed up a little.   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I assumed using the new electric blanket would result in an increase in our power consumption, however the energy monitor proved me wrong! &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Having the electric blanket on for 30min used about 0.1KWh while boiling 1L of hot water to fill at hot water bottle used about 0.16KWh of energy, 60% more! Also the electric blanket does a much better job of warming the bed then the hot water bottle, after 30min it was almost uncomfortably hot even with an ambient temperature in the room of 11 degrees! &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<br /><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-PRWQK4f8cpM/VIFxhBOblbI/AAAAAAABAjg/B0fmE75iFEs/s1600/blanket.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-PRWQK4f8cpM/VIFxhBOblbI/AAAAAAABAjg/B0fmE75iFEs/s1600/blanket.png" height="456" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;200W Electric Blanket on for about 30 min&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-9WhNqhDkTyk/VIWOeVUmd6I/AAAAAAABAro/XBAaAxspyKg/s1600/Screenshot%2B2014-12-08%2Bat%2B11.38.19.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-9WhNqhDkTyk/VIWOeVUmd6I/AAAAAAABAro/XBAaAxspyKg/s1600/Screenshot%2B2014-12-08%2Bat%2B11.38.19.png" height="286" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Kettle heating 1L of water to boiling&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Snowdonia household energy study, exploring zero carbon solutions]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/11/snowdonia-household-energy-study/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T12:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/11/snowdonia-household-energy-study</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of years ago Glyn and I and a friend of ours Bethan Gritten carried out an energy study with a local organisation called EcoBro of 17 households in Snowdonia, North Wales including our own.<br /><br />We looked at the energy used by each household for electric, heating and transport and what the effect would be of applying the solutions outlined in both <a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/">ZeroCarbonBritain</a> and <a href="http://www.withouthotair.com/">Sustainable energy without the hot air</a>, visualising the result using David MacKay’s energy stack graphics.<br /><br />I’ve been looking again at this work recently as I find it a really useful  and tangible way of looking at the energy problem and I’ve taken the opportunity to improve the energy stack graphic visualisation and put it up online here:<br /><br /><b>Dynamic visualisation: </b><br /><a href="http://egni.ecobro.org/data">http://egni.ecobro.org/data</a><br /><br />The code for it is open source and on github here:<br /><a href="https://github.com/TrystanLea/energystacks">https://github.com/TrystanLea/energystacks</a><br /><br />Here’s a brief run through of what you can see:<br /><br /><b>Current Energy Use</b><br />This first graphic shows each households current energy use and where that energy is used:<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-3My6GQ159Bo/VG5sgwDxuVI/AAAAAAAAMIw/q7vJ1EF6nvY/s1600/0present.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-3My6GQ159Bo/VG5sgwDxuVI/AAAAAAAAMIw/q7vJ1EF6nvY/s1600/0present.png" height="282" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />24% of the energy used by the households come from renewable sources, whether biomass or 100% green electricity tariffs. The wide range of total energy use per household is quite interesting, using the dynamic tool you can explore the contribution of occupancy and floor area. You can also look at C02 and energy cost per household.<br /><br /><b>Solutions for reaching 100% sustainable energy for household electric, heating and transport.</b><br /><br />In both the ZeroCarbonBritain report and David MacKay’s Sustainable  Energy without the hot air, building retrofit (insulation and  air-tightness), heatpumps and electric vehicles form the cornerstone’s of  both significantly reducing the amount of energy we need to provide the  same amount of comfort/utility and making it possible to power the  remaining energy demand from electricity generated by sustainable energy.<br /><br />The following graphics show’s what the effect would be if each household in the study applied these measures:<br /><br /><b>1) All households switch current electric consumption to a 100% Green Electricity tariff:</b><br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-HAjBniXZgCk/VG5sqcRnTTI/AAAAAAAAMI4/wUTAyUOrzEc/s1600/1greenelec.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-HAjBniXZgCk/VG5sqcRnTTI/AAAAAAAAMI4/wUTAyUOrzEc/s1600/1greenelec.png" height="283" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><b>2) 100% green electric powered heatpumps, Biomass and electric cooking instead of oil, gas and coal. </b>For heatpumps it assumes replacing existing heat input with a heatpump with a COP of 3.0. See step 5 for a very basic application of building performance retrofit work.<br /><br />Heatpumps form the cornerstone of supplying the remaining heat demand  after retrofit in both Zero Carbon Britain and David MacKay’s  sustainable energy without the hot air. The performance of a heatpump is highly dependent of course on being designed, installed and controlled correctly.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-cBsMQMzhm1M/VG5s1Wd8BqI/AAAAAAAAMJA/3BXvVWkJHUg/s1600/2heating.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-cBsMQMzhm1M/VG5s1Wd8BqI/AAAAAAAAMJA/3BXvVWkJHUg/s1600/2heating.png" height="282" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><b>3) Switch all petrol and diesel cars to electric cars powered by renewable electricity </b>(Assuming mileage stays constant and an electric car performance of 4.0 Miles/kWh)<br /><br />The ZeroCarbonBritain report from CAT suggests a reduction in the number  of miles driven through a combination of increased use of pubic  transport, walking, biking and better planning of where we live in  relation to work/activities in addition to a switch to electric vehicles  which are both more efficient than petrol and diesel cars and can be  powered by renewable electricity.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-lcZ0NG6-YWc/VG5tQICN2xI/AAAAAAAAMJI/LA2FrARb0CQ/s1600/3electriccars.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-lcZ0NG6-YWc/VG5tQICN2xI/AAAAAAAAMJI/LA2FrARb0CQ/s1600/3electriccars.png" height="283" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><b>4) Electric trains instead of planes:</b><br /><br />In order to achieve the last 15% and still enjoy travelling long  distances we would need a switch from flights to electric train  journey’s, the model here just assumes that the number of flight miles  are replaced with electric train miles powered by renewable electricity and that the destination is reachable by train.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-69_K4jfM7Ik/VG5vP_2zs7I/AAAAAAAAMJc/-5hyXVWq_eM/s1600/4electrictrains.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-69_K4jfM7Ik/VG5vP_2zs7I/AAAAAAAAMJc/-5hyXVWq_eM/s1600/4electrictrains.png" height="282" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><br /><b>5) At least 120 kWh/m2.year primary energy for space heating and home electric.</b><br /><br />Improving the thermal performance of buildings by adding insulation and  improving the air-tightness should be one of the first measures applied  and considered before or at the same time as any heating system changes as in step 2 above. The implementation of applying retrofit measures in the energy stack visualisation model here is only to set a maximum primary energy use requirement rather than to explore what’s possible on a house by house basis which would give a better picture of the potential savings from retrofit work.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-KCL_Q5nWXLE/VG5tb3QwaTI/AAAAAAAAMJQ/kPdsojZwA0w/s1600/5buildingefficiency.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-KCL_Q5nWXLE/VG5tb3QwaTI/AAAAAAAAMJQ/kPdsojZwA0w/s1600/5buildingefficiency.png" height="281" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><br /><b>Powering Up with Renewable Energy</b><br /><br />The ZeroCarbonBritain report goes into a lot of detail on how the remaining energy demand after applying power down measures can be supplied by renewable energy and also the need for storage technologies to manage the intermittent nature of a fully renewable energy supply. We didnt look into this as part of our study but it would be interesting to explore it in more detail in the future to answer questions such as: what scale of community energy projects such as community wind, solar and hydro should we be thinking of if we are to supply our energy demands after applying power down measures? and how much should we be thinking about energy storage in a more local context?<br /><br />There’s a lot of things that could be improved about the study.  Rather than applying back of the envelope calculations on the effects  of applying the various solutions to each house it would be better to look at each house in detail, carrying out a full detailed Carbon Coop home energy assessment for each house on how energy demand can be reduced by up to 70% through retrofit work.<br /><br /><b>Related links</b><br /><br />OpenEnergyMonitor page on Sustainable Energy:<br /><a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/sustainable-energy">http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/sustainable-energy</a><br /><br />The ZeroCarbonBritain report:<br /><a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/">http://zerocarbonbritain.org/</a><br /><a href="http://vimeo.com/album/2648454/video/81962195">Alice Hooker-Stroud, Centre for Alternative Technology, ‘Zero Carbon Britain (Energy)’</a> <br /><br />Sustainable energy without the hot air <br /><a href="http://withouthotair.com/">http://withouthotair.com/</a><br /><br />Carbon Coop<br /><a href="http://vimeo.com/album/2648454/video/81956917">Charlie Baker’s talk about carbon coop and 80% retrofit at the radical emissions reduction conference</a><br /><br /><br /><b>Where next?</b><br />I would be interested to hear any thoughts on how to develop this work further, where it should go next. Feel free to email me if you have any ideas or would like to discuss: trystanlea at openenergymonitor.org</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Faire Maus! A 'fair' USB optical mouse]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/09/faire-maus/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T15:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/09/faire-maus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago I wrote a <a href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/08/ethical-and-sustainable-electronics.html">blog post about ethical and sustainable electronics</a>.<br /><br />In the post I mentioned a German project called <a href="https://www.nager-it.de/en">Nager IT</a> who have designed an optical USB mouse using low carbon materials and have gone to great lengths to source ethically produced components with a transparent supply chain and exploitation free manufacture.<br /><br />We have decided to support the Nager IT project by becoming a UK reseller of their ‘Faire Maus’ or fair mouse. This mouse is as good as it gets at the moment in terms of ethical and sustainable electronics.<br /><br /><i>The mouse is a well-made three-button USB optical scroll wheel mouse made using low carbon materials, ethically produced components with a transparent supply chain and exploitation free manufacture.</i><br /><br />The mouse is now available for purchase on a non profit basis (for us) in our shop: <a href="http://shop.openenergymonitor.com/fair-usb-optical-mouse/">http://shop.openenergymonitor.com/fair-usb-optical-mouse/</a><br /><br />&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-7sdg6VzJAtE/UjckC6z5G9I/AAAAAAAAkMM/OE4NglI0Nkw/s1600/NagerIT+flyer1.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="452" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-7sdg6VzJAtE/UjckC6z5G9I/AAAAAAAAkMM/OE4NglI0Nkw/s640/NagerIT+flyer1.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-SGiD5PHvM0E/UjckC3mlDdI/AAAAAAAAkMQ/x2hp4S_ruUQ/s1600/NagerITflyer2.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="450" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-SGiD5PHvM0E/UjckC3mlDdI/AAAAAAAAkMQ/x2hp4S_ruUQ/s640/NagerITflyer2.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<em style="margin: 0px; outline: none; padding: 0px;"><strong style="margin: 0px; outline: none; padding: 0px;"><br /></strong></em>&lt;/div&gt;The mice are assembled by hand in Germany and feel very well made, the texture of the wood plastic enclosure feels good in the hand and the sleek and rubbery USB cable runs smoothy over the table.<br />&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-wsoOK0yG8U8/UjckqjNUlWI/AAAAAAAAkMc/geznhTZCmQU/s1600/2013_08_29_16.39.32__74936.1379344820.1280.1280.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="240" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-wsoOK0yG8U8/UjckqjNUlWI/AAAAAAAAkMc/geznhTZCmQU/s320/2013_08_29_16.39.32__74936.1379344820.1280.1280.jpg" width="320" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;<br />Every time I use the mouse it it reminds me that ethical and sustainable electronics is a goal which is worth pursuing.<br /><br /><i>Purchasing a fair mouse can be thought of like purchasing fair trade coffee; it might cost a little bit extra but you know that your doing good.</i><br />&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;Checkout the <a href="https://www.nager-it.de/static/pdf/en_lieferkette.pdf">great graphic</a> Nager IT have produced illustrating their transparent supply chain behind this mouse.<br />&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PMWAqYm35nk/UjclPvTHpdI/AAAAAAAAkMk/iogDpL-pMA8/s1600/2013-08-29+16.39.51.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="240" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PMWAqYm35nk/UjclPvTHpdI/AAAAAAAAkMk/iogDpL-pMA8/s320/2013-08-29+16.39.51.jpg" width="320" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="background-color: white; font-family: Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: 13.333333969116211px; line-height: 1.3; outline: none; padding: 0px;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;<br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ethical and Sustainable Electronics]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/08/ethical-and-sustainable-electronics/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-05T16:51:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/08/ethical-and-sustainable-electronics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Like many of us I love technology and enjoy using the latest gadgets, but this often sits uncomfortably on my conscience since I also care deeply about the environment and try and do my best to reduce my energy consumption and carbon footprint where possible.<br /><br />The choices we make as consumers do make a difference, the stuff we buy accounts for about 40% of our current energy consumption, this is for the average person, it’s probably a fair bit higher for ‘techies’! The energy used to make the stuff we buy is more than the energy we use for personal transport and more than our energy demands for heating and cooling [1 – P.94]. Hi-tech electronic items have a large embodied energy carbon footprint and often contain ‘<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conflict_minerals">conflict materials</a>’ such as gold (contacts) , tantalum (capacitors), tungsten etc. Manufacturing a PC requires 11 times it’s own weight in raw materials to produce compared to 1-2 times for a car [1 - P.94]<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-s5Tz7wPjxGE/Uf_PptDrQyI/AAAAAAAAilc/ke5HbwNHxx8/s1600/fairtrade.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-s5Tz7wPjxGE/Uf_PptDrQyI/AAAAAAAAilc/ke5HbwNHxx8/s1600/fairtrade.png" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Fair Trade Graphic from<a href="https://www.nager-it.de/"> Nager IT</a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />In many areas of purchasing there is an ethical and lower carbon choice available, like buying local vegetables and fair trade coffee and chocolate etc. However when purchasing electronic items I have always assumed there was not this option, that no product is more ethical or lower carbon than another (they are all just as bad!).<br /><br />I would like to highlight two projects that I have discovered lately that are working together to try and improve the state of electronics manufacture. I should state that I have no connection with these projects other than reading their websites.<br /><br />The first is a German project called <a href="https://www.nager-it.de/">Nager-IT</a> who have produced a “Faire Maus” or Fair Mouse.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-jmQRDDomW9s/Uf_P9t2clLI/AAAAAAAAilk/TBnjfnXwij8/s1600/Selection_013.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="166" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-jmQRDDomW9s/Uf_P9t2clLI/AAAAAAAAilk/TBnjfnXwij8/s400/Selection_013.png" width="400" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;They have designed the USB mouse using low carbon materials and have gone to great lengths to source ethically produced components and have pushed for transparency throughout the supply chain (something which is almost non existent in electronic production at the moment). Checkout this graphic they have produced illustrating their transparent supply chain:<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-AMlYMCcldb8/Uf_PgrvqRiI/AAAAAAAAilU/bLrPgStjcHg/s1600/Selection_011.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="451" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-AMlYMCcldb8/Uf_PgrvqRiI/AAAAAAAAilU/bLrPgStjcHg/s640/Selection_011.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><br /> The mouse they have produced can be purchased through their website.<br /><br />The second project is called <a href="http://www.fairphone.com/">FairPhone</a>, they are a social enterprise in the Netherlands with the aim of “ designing, creating and producing our first smartphone and taking the next crucial step in uncovering the story behind the sourcing, production, distribution and recycling of electronics.” They are developing and aiming to start stating in Autumn this year a ‘fairer’ Android powered smartphone.<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PbaEgV1ASFc/Uf_RSG6iEyI/AAAAAAAAil0/4r4F86OWAcA/s1600/Selection_018.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="640" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PbaEgV1ASFc/Uf_RSG6iEyI/AAAAAAAAil0/4r4F86OWAcA/s640/Selection_018.png" width="569" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Graphic from <a href="http://www.fairphone.com/">http://www.fairphone.com</a> website&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />It’s uplifting to hear of small independent companies taking on the big players in the consumer electronics industry by offering a ‘fairer’ alternative. We as consumers should do our best to show that there is demand for more ethically produced electronic projects.<br /><br />I have also discovered that <a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/campaigns/climate-change/cool-it/Campaign-analysis/Guide-to-Greener-Electronics/">GreenPeace produce an independent ranking of the large electronic companies</a> based on how ‘green’ they are.<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/--5cgWv5gzYM/Uf_YWErGBtI/AAAAAAAAimE/47DhvhCTJcY/s1600/GG_1012_bg.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="240" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/--5cgWv5gzYM/Uf_YWErGBtI/AAAAAAAAimE/47DhvhCTJcY/s640/GG_1012_bg.jpg" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Graphic from <a href="http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/campaigns/climate-change/cool-it/Campaign-analysis/Guide-to-Greener-Electronics/">GreenPeace</a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br /><br />[1] – <a href="http://www.withouthotair.com/">Sustainable Energy Without the Hot Air</a> – David MacKay [2009]<br />&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h2&gt;How this relates to OpenEnergyMonitor &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Steps we have taken so far&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Choose RHOS and components which are free of conflict materials&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Choose <a href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2012/05/embodied-energy-of-electronic-enclosure.html">low embodied energy materials for enclosures which can be easily recycled</a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use standard parts which can be easily re programmed and used for other purposes in the future&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use recyclable packaging (paper bags which are naturally antistatic) for our shipping &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Choose low power equipment, LED lighting, recycled paper for our office and switch things off at the end of the day! &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Choose surface freight (boat) rather than planes to ship stock (mainly power adapters) from China, this takes 3 months rather than 3 days but worth it for the 32 times less energy consumed [1 - P.92]. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Choose a <a href="http://www.sticklebackuk.co.uk/uk-manufacturing/">PCB manufacture</a> who are based in the UK who uses lead free techniques, complies to the highest environmental industry standard and is actively investing in techniques and equipment to reduce wastage and environmental impact (e.g water treatment and recycling) &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Strive to optimise electrical consumption in our hardware to be as low was possible &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Steps we would like to take in the future &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Produce an end-to-end supply chain map of our manufacture (possibly using http://sourcemap.com)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Try and calculate the embodied energy that goes into producing our designs and constantly try and find ways we can reduce this&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sell through local distributors to reduce air based shipping and investigate possibility of local manufacture&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use recycled plastic / other low embodied energy martial in the moulding of the housing for our next version of the emonGLCD and temperature monitoring node &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Investigate how we can build recyclability into the design, checkout the video below from the <a href="http://www.greatrecovery.org.uk/">Great Recovery Project</a>:&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/0ExzD-79aXw" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
