<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: renewable | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/renewable/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-03T09:40:31+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Year of Solar PV Monitoring]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/05/one-year-of-solar-pv-monitoring/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-13T20:27:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/05/one-year-of-solar-pv-monitoring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">On the 23rd November 2011 we have had a 2.9Kwp solar PV installed.&nbsp;</div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-6Zd9PL-5AJE/UZEzH7aGB9I/AAAAAAAAeog/-tocRt1M_OA/s1600/Panels.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="177" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-6Zd9PL-5AJE/UZEzH7aGB9I/AAAAAAAAeog/-tocRt1M_OA/s320/Panels.png" width="320" /></a></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">We recently got our first payment from the<a href="http://www.fitariffs.co.uk/eligible/levels/">&nbsp;UK's&nbsp;governments&nbsp;Feed In Tariff</a>&nbsp;scheme.&nbsp;This has prompted me to take stock of how the system has been performing and how the data collected using the OpenEnergyMonitor energy monitoring system compares to the utility&nbsp;company's&nbsp;billing meter:</div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both;">From the 23rd Nov 2011 - 23rd Nov 2012 the billing utility meter on the solar PV system has recorded a &nbsp;<b>generation of 2069 kWh</b>. Over the same period we consumed 3588&nbsp;Kwh, <b>57% of our electrical energy needs have been met by the solar PV.&nbsp;</b></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">At this rate it looks like we're on track for the system to pay back in 7-8 years, maybe even less if we have some more sun in the next few years, fingers crossed!&nbsp;</div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">For the same time period the OpenEnergyMonitor monitoring system has recorded a generation of 2029 kWh, giving the <b>energy monitor an accuracy of 98%!&nbsp;</b></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">The monitoring system is a standard&nbsp;<a href="http://shop.openenergymonitor.com/solar-pv-monitor-kit-bundle-433mhz-euro-plug/">emonTx with an AC-AC adapter taking Real Power readings</a>.&nbsp;</div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-BSjVQR4ViYY/UZFElq6OGdI/AAAAAAAAeow/VV4iTj7-PmI/s1600/Selection_014.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="276" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-BSjVQR4ViYY/UZFElq6OGdI/AAAAAAAAeow/VV4iTj7-PmI/s640/Selection_014.png" width="640" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">One Year of PV Generation</td></tr></tbody></table>
<table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-aBI-v-iDQ9Q/UZHtMP1ludI/AAAAAAAAepM/zz59PUGZ0lE/s1600/Selection_015.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="228" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-aBI-v-iDQ9Q/UZHtMP1ludI/AAAAAAAAepM/zz59PUGZ0lE/s640/Selection_015.png" width="640" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">Kwh/d Electricity Consumption (orange) Overlaid&nbsp;with Generation (blue)&nbsp;</td></tr></tbody></table>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">When the system was installed the solar PV company&nbsp;estimated&nbsp;we would produce&nbsp;2434 Kwh per year, we generated 15% less than this estimate. This could partly be&nbsp;attributed&nbsp;to the very poor summer we&nbsp;experienced&nbsp;in 2012.</div>
<div><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Arial, Verdana, sans-serif; font-size: 13px;"><br /></span></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">This year is already looking promising, on the 2nd of May 2013 our system generated a record (for us) of 18.3 Kwh 1.9 times more than we consumed on that day (9.7 Kwh):</div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-XTd1UQbWGI4/UZEv6lkOiTI/AAAAAAAAeoU/EFmdCDAIG9I/s1600/New+PV+record+2nd+May+2013.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="640" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-XTd1UQbWGI4/UZEv6lkOiTI/AAAAAAAAeoU/EFmdCDAIG9I/s640/New+PV+record+2nd+May+2013.png" width="451" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">Record Generation on 2nd May 2013</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>Fingers crossed for a sunny 2013 summer!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Update on progress and a revised aim]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2009/07/update-on-progress-and-revised-aim/"/>
    <updated>2009-07-26T17:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2009/07/update-on-progress-and-revised-aim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First an update on what I’ve been working on and where I hope to go next.<br /><br />Over the last few weeks I have been working on monitoring mains AC electricity energy use with the non invasive current transformer method rather than the invasive current sensing resistor method. In my previous post on the current transformer (CT) method I made two errors first the circuit I used was over complicated and secondly the efergy energy monitor seems to be able to estimate real power. Even though the CT method only measures current, I tried to see if it was possible to infer the voltage waveform from the current waveform producing a close estimate of the real power, It seems to have worked quite well. I will upload the details of what I have done soon.<br /><br />I have also been working on DC energy monitoring for the wind turbine. I built the circuit that I talked about in the previous post. I however managed to blow one of the amps on the LT1495 chip and there seems to be an offset on the other amp which may be due to having blown one side. Id like to find a cheaper amp to replace the LT1495, maybe sacrificing a little on accuracy.<br /><br />For the next two weeks the wind turbine is going up at two local festivals here in North Wales (Celtic camp and the National Eisteddfod). If your in the area feel free to drop by.<br /><br />After the festivals I hope to have a look at monitoring the energy captured by the hot water solar panel we have here on our house, at the moment were not sure if it is working properly, it doesn’t seem to be heating much water. However its hard to tell; the controller gives the current temperatures of the tank and panel, it would be useful to have graphs of the temperatures over several days and if a flow meter is installed it is possible to measure kWh of heat captured. Hopefully with better information it would be easier to see how well the system is working. It would be great to have a bit of software that analysed the data from the system, compared it to ideal site data and then be able to tell you something like “your system is working at 80% of potential”<br /><br />All the above applications can all share the same software and similar electronics based on the Arduino. Once one is built, your have a lot of what you need for the others.<br /><br />Further along the line it could be interesting to investigate possibilities for predicting how much energy it is possible to capture from a wind turbine or a hydro turbine before it is installed at a site using an arduino connected to an anemometer for wind or a river flow meter for hydro. I have also been doing some work with Suneil on trying to characterise how well the generator we built for the wind turbine works. With some detailed data and analysis it might be possible to identify possible improvements. Both the energy prediction and generator development could again share much of the same electronics, software and knowledge required for the energy use and energy capture parts of the project. And finally I would like to look at Internet connectivity, it would be really great to be able to check up on how say the wind turbine is doing from anyware in the world.<br /><br />And so for the project to encompass all of the above:<br /><br /><span style="font-style: italic;">“This is a project to develop and build open source energy monitoring and analysis tools for energy efficiency and distributed renewable micro generation.”</span><br /><br />The project is then divided into 6 areas:<br /><br /><span style="font-weight: bold;">Energy Use</span><br />Mains AC electricity and DC.<br /><br /><span style="font-weight: bold;">Energy Capture</span><br />Wind turbine, hot water solar, hydro etc.<br /><br /><span style="font-weight: bold;">Energy Prediction</span><br />Wind speeds, stream flow…<br /><br /><span style="font-weight: bold;">Energy Technology Development</span><br />Tools for the development and building stage rather than the use stage.<br /><br /><span style="font-weight: bold;">Data graphing and analysis and storage.</span><br />Using free and open source software<br /><br /><span style="font-weight: bold;">Sharing data with the world</span><br />Internet connectivity.<br /><br />Hopefully this better reflects the direction of the work and will hopefully be a more useful collection of tools for anyone interested.<br /><br />I will be updating the website soon with the recent work and to reflect the revised aim.<br /><br />Any comments on the above would be great. Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
