<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: dashboard | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/dashboard/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-25T16:34:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New MyElectric Emoncms app, realtime power graph and energy totals]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/07/new-myelectric-app-realtime-power-graph/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-30T15:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/07/new-myelectric-app-realtime-power-graph</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><br /><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-YHIAud8fvlg/Vbo1wbdWU3I/AAAAAAAATqI/zORntneXFnM/s1600/newmyelectric.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="400" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-YHIAud8fvlg/Vbo1wbdWU3I/AAAAAAAATqI/zORntneXFnM/s400/newmyelectric.png" width="281" /></a><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-zX3yeWqv0Ug/Vbo10IpEtBI/AAAAAAAATqQ/lm637JsnEbg/s1600/SAM_0929.JPG" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="400" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-zX3yeWqv0Ug/Vbo10IpEtBI/AAAAAAAATqQ/lm637JsnEbg/s400/SAM_0929.JPG" width="300" /> </a><br /><br />The MyElectric app has long been needing some work so that it both provides more useful information and also reports the daily kwh data correctly for different timezones and when the app is used as an always on display and the day changes.<br /><br />There is now a new version available that adds a real-time power graph as well as totals for the week, month, year and all time and the daily kwh bar graph as before.<br /><br />To generate the kWh per day graph this version focuses on supporting feeds either created with the “power to kWh” processor or “Wh accumulator” processor rather than the “power to kWh/d” processor and average power feeds. Trying to support each one was leading to quite a lot of bugs in addition to more fundamental issues with time zones present with the power to Kwh/d daily feed approach. <br /><br />The “power to kWh” and “Wh accumulator” processors are both fully supported on the emonPi and emonBase running the low-write image. There’s more on how this accumulating watt hour or kWh approach works here: <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/3995">Development: Calculating Wh totals on the emontx</a><br /><br />I now have the new MyElectric app running alongside the MySolarPV app in my home and I’m really quite pleased with the results. The totals at the bottom and average kWh per day for each period gives me most of what data to see at a glance how my electricity consumption is fairing and having this information available on a wall mounted tablet really makes all the difference compared with having to login to emoncms on my computer to see the data.<br /><br />I would like to make it easier to switch in between the different apps, a side swipe would be really nice. I would also like to look into a way to make it possible to download apps from an app repository from within emoncms itself so that new apps could be added without them having to be in the app repository on github, there’s quite a bit of work needed to get there thought.<br /><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improved my solar application specific dashboard for tablet energy display's]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/07/improved-my-solar-application-specific/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-02T14:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/07/improved-my-solar-application-specific</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With my <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2015/06/using-tablet-as-wall-mount-energy.html">Refurbished Samsung Galexy Tab 3</a> energy display up and running I’ve made a few changes to the solarPV application specific dashboard to make it work better. Thanks to Steve for many of the suggestions, see <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/10842">forum post. </a><br />&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The view now automatically updates as a rolling window, in any of the modes, 3 hour, 6 hour, day etc &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The balance Import/Export is now the same size as the solar &amp; house consumption. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Night time noise on the solar pv channel less than 10W is zeroed. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The in-window stats are now easier to see at a distance with larger font.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The view buttons are easier to click on a touch screen.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Its possible to make up the consumption or solar generation feed from multiple feeds on the fly by entering comma separated feed id’s in the configuration interface.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;Here’s the result:<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-D8H9FPRL4Z4/VZVPrLN7TMI/AAAAAAAATRw/mg9SZgro_CA/s1600/IMG_7255.JPG" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="426" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-D8H9FPRL4Z4/VZVPrLN7TMI/AAAAAAAATRw/mg9SZgro_CA/s640/IMG_7255.JPG" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><strong>Upgrading</strong><br />To upgrade on the <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/10729">emonPi or latest emonbase image</a> navigate to the  admin tab in emoncms and then click the <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/modules/emonpi#update">update button</a>. Otherwise the app’s  module can be downloaded and updated using git:<a href="http://github.com/emoncms/app" title="http://github.com/emoncms/app"> http://github.com/emoncms/app</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
