<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Course/Workshop | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/course-slash-workshop/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-25T12:56:59+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Carbon Coop]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/05/carbon-coop/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-03T15:27:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/05/carbon-coop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The weekend before last I went to Manchester to help Matt Fawcett and Jonathan Atkinson of Carbon coop with the <a href="http://carbon.coop/news/2013-04-03/ecohome-lab-launch-workshop-build-day-first-meet">EcoHome_Lab</a> openenergymonitor energy monitor building workshop. I haven’t blogged about Carbon Co-op before so Id like to give a bit of an intro to who they are and why I think what they are doing is particularly exiting.<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-bAdkFqme1Bk/UYPA0JtMAkI/AAAAAAAACks/fuLZUpwBCdc/s1600/2013-04-26+12.56.04.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="188" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-bAdkFqme1Bk/UYPA0JtMAkI/AAAAAAAACks/fuLZUpwBCdc/s640/2013-04-26+12.56.04.jpg" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://carbon.coop/">http://carbon.coop</a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;I first met <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/user/1510">Matt</a> who is responsible for the monitoring at Carbon Coop at a <a href="http://www.cleanweb.org.uk/">Cleanwebuk</a> event in London after initially exchanging a few emails. Matt explained that they are working on a retrofit programme to try to prove that it is possible to cut between 60-80% of energy demand from homes because this is what we need to save.<br />&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;<br />They want monitoring to be at the centre of everything they do, so that their members can see how minor changes impact energy usage as well as more major retrofit changes. They also want to monitor internal air quality as well as temperature for early identification of any problems with the insulation and airtightness measures. By monitoring humidity, CO2 as well as temperature Matt explained that its possible to isolate issues around damp/cooking etc from issues around ventilation.<br /><br />They are really keen to use open source technology because that then gives them the freedom to configure the system as they need and then get at the data. They are keen advocates for open data and open source software and hardware in general and carry out their own work in an open way.<br /><br />Since then Carbon Coop have installed 18 openenergymonitor energy monitors in houses across Manchester, held two energy monitor workshops including last weekends and are going forward with retrofitting 15 houses to between 60 and 80% carbon reduction.<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-CoqTigz4lPg/UYPCMIHSV2I/AAAAAAAACk4/lJrln547-Uc/s1600/2013-04-20+14.25.30.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><img border="0" height="180" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-CoqTigz4lPg/UYPCMIHSV2I/AAAAAAAACk4/lJrln547-Uc/s640/2013-04-20+14.25.30.jpg" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Building monitors at the Carbon Coop EcoHomeLab workshop 19th-20th April &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;What I really like about Carbon Coop is the way they are working on every part of the process: They start with the larger picture of what we need to do in terms of sustainable energy in housing and then go from there to work on an individual household basis, first carrying out a detailed whole house assessment based on the governments SAP (standard assessment procedure) to identify where most energy is being lost, which improvements would have the biggest effect and what to do first. They’re using the energy monitoring to provide feedback to households as described above. From there they go on to help households carry out work on their houses, from finding the best way to finance retrofit measures to working with architects and local tradespeople. Once the retrofit building works are complete they continue to monitor to ensure that the changes reach the predicted energy targets. They do all this using an open source approach, they are also a co-operative that is open for people to join. They are a really switched on group of people, carrying out their work in a thorough, thoughtful, evidence based way.<br /><br />Every-time I go to visit them I come back inspired to develop things further. One of the highlights of the last visit was listening to Eleni Kalkantzi who works for URBED (Carbon Coop’s technical partner) talk about the whole house assessment methodology and reports she, Charlie Baker and Marianne Heaslip have developed. A huge amount of work has clearly gone into these reports and the assessment method, they have an example report and report on the assessment method here:<br /><br />See their example assessment here: <a href="http://carbon.coop/assessments/CC_EXAMPLE_ASSESSMENT2.pdf">http://carbon.coop/assessments/CC_EXAMPLE_ASSESSMENT2.pdf</a><br /><br />Report on the assessment method: <a href="http://carbon.coop/assessments/URBED_ASSESSMENT_REPORT.pdf">http://carbon.coop/assessments/URBED_ASSESSMENT_REPORT.pdf</a><br /><br />They see the next step being to integrate monitoring data directly in to the SAP model on which their reporting is based to reduce the number of assumptions made. This is where the <a href="http://github.com/emoncms/sap">open source emoncms SAP model</a> that we have been developing comes in but I will come back to that in another post.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pictures from the OpenEnergyMonitor CAT course]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/04/pictures-from-openenergymonitor-cat/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-17T20:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/04/pictures-from-openenergymonitor-cat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">A couple of weeks ago we held our first openenergymonitor course at the Center for Alternative Technology in Mid Wales. It was well attended with 17 of us in total including tutors: myself, Carlos and Suneil. We where also lucky to have Robin Emley come down to demo his MK2 Surplus PV diverter and lend a helping hand.</div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">Here are a few pictures of everyone getting stuck in with building emontx's and rfm12pi adapter boards:</div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-SFQZK8DQ0O0/UVn4lifvx_I/AAAAAAAACjE/MIjwWs0p-3A/s1600/2013-03-26+11.37.06.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="180" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-SFQZK8DQ0O0/UVn4lifvx_I/AAAAAAAACjE/MIjwWs0p-3A/s320/2013-03-26+11.37.06.jpg" width="320" /></a></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><br /></div>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;">Carlos and Sebastian who came all the way from Germany going through the Raspberry PI setup process:</div>
<p><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-GboPwPV_rgM/UVn4mqVr1kI/AAAAAAAACjM/ypCWHG9sGZU/s1600/2013-03-26+11.36.33.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="180" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-GboPwPV_rgM/UVn4mqVr1kI/AAAAAAAACjM/ypCWHG9sGZU/s320/2013-03-26+11.36.33.jpg" width="320" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ow3IK2F_TUI/UVn4nNmmSvI/AAAAAAAACjU/Puf7fgOlGkg/s1600/2013-03-26+11.36.16.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="180" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ow3IK2F_TUI/UVn4nNmmSvI/AAAAAAAACjU/Puf7fgOlGkg/s320/2013-03-26+11.36.16.jpg" width="320" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;Robin Emley helping out above and his solar pv diversion setup below:&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-qfJzJk8XImw/UVn4n3Y1mkI/AAAAAAAACjc/vaNf_9ZJSVI/s1600/2013-03-25+19.34.25.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="180" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-qfJzJk8XImw/UVn4n3Y1mkI/AAAAAAAACjc/vaNf_9ZJSVI/s320/2013-03-25+19.34.25.jpg" width="320" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;The course was held in the beautiful Welsh Institute for Sustainable Education (WISE)  building at CAT:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-8PEEv1-emj8/UVqYYV47qPI/AAAAAAAACjs/YKiDI59C8s8/s1600/WISE-building-at-Centre-f-007.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="192" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-8PEEv1-emj8/UVqYYV47qPI/AAAAAAAACjs/YKiDI59C8s8/s320/WISE-building-at-Centre-f-007.jpg" width="320" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both;"&gt;I’m in Manchester this coming weekend (20th April) helping Matt Fawcett and the rest of the Carbon Coop team with their: <a href="http://carbon.coop/news/2013-04-03/ecohome-lab-launch-workshop-build-day-first-meet">Ecohome lab launch workshop and build day</a>. Looking forward to it.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;<br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Course at the Centre for Alternative Technology]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/03/course-at-centre-for-alternative/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-02T23:21:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/03/course-at-centre-for-alternative</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>by Carlos Alonso Gabizón<br />&lt;h2&gt;<style type="text/css"> &lt;!--   @page { margin: 2cm }   P { margin-bottom: 0.21cm }  </style> Open Source Tools For Energy Monitoring&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;25th - 28th March&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3 style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;When working towards sustainable energy it is important that we work towards it in a way that adds up. Energy monitoring is a vital tool for helping us do this from measuring our home electricity consumption to working out the performance of sustainable heating systems.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;During this short workshop we will explore and build monitoring solutions that are based on open source technology developed as part of the openenergymonitor.org online research project. Solutions that can be configured for a wide range of applications including:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Household Electricity monitoring&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Heat-pump monitoring&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Solar PV generation monitoring&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;The workshop will focus around a practical case study of monitoring electricity generation and use at the Centre for Alternative Technology designing a public energy display to engage visitors that can be accessed both at the site and on the web.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;Workshop content outline&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-QFgtAhsvzMA/UTKHc6opBhI/AAAAAAAAACE/WG9p-nDTiCs/s1600/content_outline.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="376" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-QFgtAhsvzMA/UTKHc6opBhI/AAAAAAAAACE/WG9p-nDTiCs/s640/content_outline.jpg" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt; &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Course tutors&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;<i><b>Carlos Alonso Gabizón</b></i> – Is the course leader. Worked on microgrid energy display project at CAT and open source software for extracting energy data from PV inverter equipment. Carlos has an electronic engineering and computer science background.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;<i><b>Trystan Lea</b></i> – As a core developer on the openenergymonitor project Trystan will be introducing the hardware and software workshops. Trystan codeveloped with Glyn Hudson many of the main elements of the openenergymonitor system with a focus on software and firmware including emoncms an open source web application for energy visualisation. Trystan also runs the openenergymonitor kit shop with Glyn Hudson.Trystan has a Physics background with a BSc in Physics at Cardiff University.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;<i><b>Suneil Tagore</b></i> – Will be giving an introduction to open source 3D fabrication/printing using the reprap. Suneil has also worked on DC monitoring for theHugh Piggot wind turbine. Suneil has a background in Engineering andcomputer science with an MEng in Engineering at UCL London and a MSc inComputer Science at Cardiff University.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Course cost and how to book&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;The course cost is £520. Concession: £340 (unemployed, retired or full time student). This covers accommodation, food and course tuition.<br />You can reserve a place on the course online at: <a href="http://courses.cat.org.uk/energyrenewables/open-source-tools-for-energy-monitoring-detail" target="_blank">courses.cat.org.uk/</a> or by phone calling the CAT Courses Department on 01654 704 952.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h4&gt;What will you get from this course?&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom: 0cm;"&gt;Firstly, the knowledge and practical skills to build and set up a monitor solution based in the openenergymonitor kit and how to expand its functionality beyond what is done in the course.<br />Secondly, you will be able to install emonCMS, set it up and create really nice visualizations.<br />And lastly but more exciting than the previous, you will take home your own energy monitor completely ready to use!!!&lt;/div&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
