<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: zerocarbonbritain | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/zerocarbonbritain/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-08T18:29:22+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Understanding zero carbon energy systems: Energy storage (part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/08/understanding-zero-carbon-energy/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-02T08:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/08/understanding-zero-carbon-energy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last zero carbon energy model example in the series investigating the matching between different energy demands and a variable renewable supply reached 89% supply/demand matching with a mixture of solar and wind supply, traditional electricity demand, space heating with heatpumps, electric vehicles with smart charging and two small stores one 7 kWh li-ion store and one 10 kWh heatstore.<br /><br />Blog post: <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2015/07/open-source-hourly-zero-carbon-energy.html">Open source hourly zero carbon energy model, combining traditional electric, heating and electric vehicle demand.</a><br /><br />How do we achieve that final 10% of supply/demand matching? Is it possible to just scale up the li-ion storage or do we need something else? What is the nature of that final unmet demand and the final storage requirement?<br /><br />One of the good things about having the model written as a program rather than spreadsheet is that its really easy to run the model iteratively for different input values, you can quickly go through hundreds of model runs. You don’t need to manually run the model for each value. <br /><br />The following graph shows how the percentage of supply/demand matching increases as the storage size increases. The python source code for the model used to produce this can be found here: <a href="https://github.com/TrystanLea/zcem/blob/master/python/storagerequirements.py">https://github.com/TrystanLea/zcem/blob/master/python/storagerequirements.py</a><br /><br />In order to capture all of the storage requirement in this analysis the heatstore was removed from the <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.co.uk/2015/07/open-source-hourly-zero-carbon-energy.html">last model</a> and the EV charging was set to a constant charge profile rather than smart charging. This configuration achieves 78.3% supply/demand matching with no storage, an unmet electricity demand of 13,628 kWh over 10 years out of a total of 62,771 kWh.<br /><br />% Supply/demand matching vs storage size in kWh:<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-Abx9aCP9W7c/Vb3YfvwKL2I/AAAAAAAATrM/vQvu6kMp3n8/s1600/matchingvsstoresize.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="384" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-Abx9aCP9W7c/Vb3YfvwKL2I/AAAAAAAATrM/vQvu6kMp3n8/s640/matchingvsstoresize.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;We can see clearly that the degree of supply/demand matching increases very quickly as we add the first kWh’s of storage but then the gains taper off quickly requiring orders of magnitude more storage to reach the final 5%.<br /><br />The first 10% of supply/demand matching, bringing us up to 90% needs around 25 kWh of storage. The next 5% up to 95% requires an additional 120 kWh of storage. The final 5% requires 1536 kWh.<br /><br /><b>Note:</b> see added section below for calculations of total storage capacity required if the oversupply is 20% or 30% instead of the 4% here.<br /><br />The first 1.5% of the storage capacity provides 50% of the required supply/demand matching gain.<br /><br />Its interesting to look at what the use of the 1680 kWh store looks like across the 10 year model period:<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-nhFBpcMlbbo/Vb3Y0qBKDgI/AAAAAAAATrc/G1vtEdv6ts0/s1600/storeSOC.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="358" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-nhFBpcMlbbo/Vb3Y0qBKDgI/AAAAAAAATrc/G1vtEdv6ts0/s640/storeSOC.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;The store is used most over winter, where electricity demand is highest due to heatpump space heating. We can see that the winters of 2010 and 2011 where particularly cold and that the extent of the storage requirement in this model is largely driven by these successive harsh winters and a less strong summer. If the modelling had only considered 2002 to 2010 we might have under specified the storage amount needed by half which highlights the importance of modelling over as many years as possible.<br /><br /><b>Utilisation, cycling</b><br /><br />We can see roughly that the full extent of the store is only used once in 10 years and is largely needed to cover just 3.5 months at the start of 2011. Even if the store was half its size it would only be used fully 3 times in 10 years. The extend to which the store is cycled is an important consideration in store choice, both from the perspective of wear and financial payback.<br /><br />The following graph charts annual cycle requirements vs storage size, highlighting how most of the storage requirement is cycled very infrequently. A 25 kWh store delivers the equivalent charge/discharge energy of 30 full cycles a year, 100% depth of discharge (DOD). The next 120 kWh would only be cycled 7.3 times a year. A 625 kWh store would only be cycled twice in a year and the full 1680 kWh store only 0.8 times a year.<br /><br />Cycles per year vs store size:<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-p7Wlm4jfR4U/Vb3YqXb0CLI/AAAAAAAATrU/gKPaudwDSM0/s1600/cycles.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="382" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-p7Wlm4jfR4U/Vb3YqXb0CLI/AAAAAAAATrU/gKPaudwDSM0/s640/cycles.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;The above gives us an initial degree of insight into the nature of the storage requirements and how reaching the final 10% of supply/demand matching requires magnitude more storage than the first 10%.<br /><br />Its important to note that the results above are for a model based on uk climate and weather, it would be worth repeating this kind of modelling for warmer countries where air conditioning that matched solar pv generation was a large component of demand rather than winter heating.<br /><br />The next blog post will look at some of the different storage technologies available and how they are suitable for different segments of the overall storage requirement.<br /><br /><b>Reducing storage requirements by oversupply  </b><br />Following the conversation with Dominic Zapman here <a href="https://twitter.com/Zapaman/status/627806828865409024">https://twitter.com/Zapaman/status/627806828865409024</a>, I decided to re-run the model with a higher degree of oversupply - nearer the oversupply level used by ZeroCarbonBritain. The results above are for an oversupply of 4% with 65391 kWh supplied over 10 years for a demand of 62771 kWh. A 1680 kWh store is 27% of the annual demand.<br /><br />If we re-run the model with an oversupply of 20%, 100% supply/demand matching is reached with a 676 kWh store, 11% of annual demand.<br /><br />If the oversupply is 30%, the storage requirement is reduced to 484 kWh, 8% of annual demand.<br /><br />The ZeroCarbonBritain model exports 165 TWh out of the 738 TWh generated which is an oversupply of 22%. A further 180 TWh is used to generate synthetic fuels including power to gas methane storage. A high percentage of this demand will also be oversupply. The long term power to gas storage capacity in ZCB is 60 TWh, delivering on average 14 TWh/year of backup supply covering about 402 TWh of final demand excluding exports. Delivered backup is 3.5% of final demand.<br /><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open source hourly zero carbon energy model, combining traditional electric, heating and electric vehicle demand.]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/07/open-source-hourly-zero-carbon-energy/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-04T13:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/07/open-source-hourly-zero-carbon-energy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last 6 zero carbon energy model examples (linked below) have explored the core parts of a household energy model looking at supply and demand including the electrification of space heating demand and transport demand so that it can be provided for with renewable electricity.<br /><br />This final model in this series  brings all these components together to see how the combination of  demands interact and how they affect the supply and demand matching.<br /><br />It also explores the contribution of two small scale stores a 7kWh electrical store (such as a Tesla power wall) and a 10kWh heatstore.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-BRUPMwiPZsE/VZfRMe-vH7I/AAAAAAAATSs/oZCasHAvinI/s1600/all.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="342" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-BRUPMwiPZsE/VZfRMe-vH7I/AAAAAAAATSs/oZCasHAvinI/s640/all.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;<b>The interactive modelling tool can be opened here: </b>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;<b>Online tool:</b> <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel">http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel</a> &gt; navigate to <i>7. All</i>&lt;/div&gt;<br />The following table show the results in terms of percentage of demand supplied directly of running the model with different electric vehicle charging profiles, and storage options. There is a small 4% oversupply.<br /><br />&lt;table class="table"&gt; &lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;<b>No stores</b>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + night charging&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;62.3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + 1/2day 1night charging&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;76.2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + flat charging&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;78.3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + smartcharging&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;86.3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;<b>Liion store</b>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + night charging + 7 kWh li-ion store&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;84.4%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + 1/2day 1night charging + 7 kWh li-ion store&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;86.0%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + flat charging + 7 kWh li-ion store&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;86.2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + smart charging + 7 kWh li-ion store&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;88.6%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;<b>Heatstore</b>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + night charging + 10 kWh heatstore&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;70.2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + 1/2day 1night charging + 10 kWh heatstore&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;81.0%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + flat charging + 10 kWh heatstore&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;82.4%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + smartcharging + 10 kWh heatstore&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;87.5%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;<b>Liion + heatstore</b>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + 7 kWh li-ion store + 10 kWh heatstore + nightcharging&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;85.5%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + 7 kWh li-ion store + 10 kWh heatstore + 1/2d 1n&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;86.9%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + 7 kWh li-ion store + 10 kWh heatstore + flatcharging&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;87.1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4% OS + 7 kWh li-ion store + 10 kWh heatstore + smartcharging&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;89.3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />Its interesting that a matching of 89.3% can be achieved with 7 kWh li-ion store, 10 kWh heatstore and electric car smartcharging up from a minimum of 62.3% with no stores and night time charging only. I think its quite impressive and encouraging that this high a level of matching can be achieved from a relatively small amount of storage and that 86% can be achieved with the smartcharging option only.<br /><br />There are clearly different routes possible to achieve higher degree’s of matching. If smart charging is technically possible with the flexibility used within the model and that it doesn’t provide too much of a burden on the user and only requires potentially a relatively small amount of electronics, embodied energy and cost compared to the li-ion store and heatstore then smart charging may be a more effective option.<br /><br />A li-ion store and flat rate charging provides about the same benefit as smart charging and so if smart charging does not pan out to be practical then there may be an option to make up for it with a li-ion store, especially if the embodied energy and cost of storage reduces significantly.<br /><br />The combination of measures provide smaller gains (if you apply smart charging first then the li-ion store only provides ~3% additional gains, however if you apply the li-ion first it looks like its the smart charging that only provides the small gain). Perhaps an important aspect is that a combination could provide important redundancy. It looks worthwhile to explore and develop each of the above solutions with a focus on how they integrate, the flexibility at which they can match supply, their costs and embodied energy. <br /><br />The other blog posts in this series are linked below and the next model will explore the use of large capacity energy stores such as power to gas to reach 100% supply/demand matching. All the modelling behind this work is open source and available on github here: https://github.com/TrystanLea/zcem  <br />&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2015/06/modelling-hourly-demand-and-supply-for.html">Modelling hourly demand and supply for renewable powered domestic electricity, heating with heatpumps and electric vehicles</a> &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2015/06/hourly-energy-model-example-1-variable.html">Hourly energy model example 1: Variable Supply</a> &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2015/06/hourly-energy-model-example-2-variable.html">Hourly energy model example 2: Variable supply and flat demand (python code included)</a> &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2015/06/hourly-energy-model-example-3-variable.html">Hourly energy model example 3: Variable supply and traditional electricity demand</a> &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2015/06/hourly-energy-model-example-4.html">Hourly energy model example 4: Complementarity of different renewable generating technologies</a> &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2015/06/hourly-energy-model-example-5-simple.html">Hourly energy model example 5: Simple space heating model with heatpump’s powered by renewable energy</a> &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2015/07/hourly-energy-model-example-5-electric.html">Hourly energy model example 6: Electric vehicles and a renewable energy supply</a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hourly energy model example 6: Electric vehicles and a renewable energy supply]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/07/hourly-energy-model-example-5-electric/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-02T16:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/07/hourly-energy-model-example-5-electric</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing the blog series on building a hourly zero carbon energy model based on the ZeroCarbonBritain dataset the 6th example model explores another another key solution used in the <a href="http://zerocarbonbritain.org/">ZeroCarbonBritain report</a> and in David MacKay’s book <a href="http://withouthotair.com/c21/page_146.shtml.">Sustainable energy without the hot air</a>: the electrification of transport.<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-iZQ57wiOHho/VZVjbKLf-aI/AAAAAAAATSY/Kvbzs5YuKl8/s1600/catchargingstation.jpeg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="356" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-iZQ57wiOHho/VZVjbKLf-aI/AAAAAAAATSY/Kvbzs5YuKl8/s640/catchargingstation.jpeg" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;The intention here is to explore what level of supply/demand matching between a renewable energy supply and electric vehicle charging could be achievable with different electric vehicle charging profiles. A higher level of supply/demand matching reduces the amount of backup or energy storage required to meet demand. <br /><br />The first example starts by integrating electric vehicles with a simple night time charge profile. The second example then explores more constant charge profile throughout the day – this constant charge profile could be the result of a large number of electric cars all charging at different times, some at work, others at home over night. The third example explores a basic smart charging approach where the charge rate can aligned with the availability of renewable energy. There are many people who are already choosing their charge times to align with domestic solar pv output and there is much discussion about the opportunity that this may provide for matching supply and demand.<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1VWyeRly7Y8/VZVc5Ve4M1I/AAAAAAAATSA/Y2jurkb0CmU/s1600/electricvehicle.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="328" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1VWyeRly7Y8/VZVc5Ve4M1I/AAAAAAAATSA/Y2jurkb0CmU/s640/electricvehicle.png" width="640" /> </a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;To open the examples, launch the online tool:<b> </b>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;<b><br /></b>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;<b>Online tool:</b> <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel">http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel</a> &gt; navigate to <i>6. electric vehicles</i>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Night time charging&lt;/h3&gt;The first model investigates night time charging between 1am and 8am (7 hours). The charge profile of an aggregation of electric vehicles is much more likely to be smoother than this with a distribution over the day especially as the number of work based charging facilities and rapid chargers increase but for interest we will consider this case.<br />&lt;table class="table"&gt;    &lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Onshore wind&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Offshore wind&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Wave&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Tidal&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Solar&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Installed capacity&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;0.8699&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.5864&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.9931&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.1783&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2.9825&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Percentage of demand<br />supplied directly&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;27%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;28%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;29%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;28%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Flat charging profile&lt;/h3&gt;The results of running the model for a flat demand profile is the same as the earlier example where we considered the degree of matching between supply and a flat demand. Substantial improvements in matching compared to the night time charging profile is gained by just managing to distribute the charging requirements evenly across a day. This is unlikely to be possible on a single household basis but perhaps possible when the aggregate demand of many hundred cars are taken into account with day time charging at work encouraged.<br />&lt;table class="table"&gt;    &lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Onshore wind&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Offshore wind&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Wave&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Tidal&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Solar&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Installed capacity&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;0.8699&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.5864&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.9931&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.1783&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2.9825&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Percentage of demand<br />supplied directly&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;65%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;76%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;74%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;57%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40%&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Percentage of time demand is<br />more or the same as the supply&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;40%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;46%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;45%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;38%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;32%&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Smart charging (variable rate charger that matches available supply)&lt;/h3&gt;Smart charging could allow electric vehicles that are left connected to the grid to charge when renewable electricity is available. The simple smart charging algorithm in this example starts by using available supply to charge the car’s battery directly. A minimum SOC level required to cover the days journeys is maintained with a top-up charge if needed. The battery SOC is kept between 10% and 80% to help ensure long life is maintained.<br /><br />The charge rate is based on a forecast of available supply over the next 24 hours, if the available supply is more than the forecast demand then the charge rate can be reduced. If there is twice as much supply forecast than demand then the rate of charge could by dropped to half the available supply in order to distribute the charge better across the 24h.<br />&lt;table class="table"&gt;    &lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Onshore wind&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Offshore wind&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Wave&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Tidal&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Solar&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Installed capacity&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;0.8699&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.5864&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.9931&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.1783&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2.9825&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Percentage of demand<br />supplied directly&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;78.7%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;85.3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;80.3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;84.1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;72.2%&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Percentage of time demand is<br />more or the same as the supply&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;69.5%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;74.5%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;67.5%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;76.1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;69.2%&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />The results show substantial improvements again for the addition of smart charging, with smart charging + solar showing the largest gain. It is notable that the model suggests that a 2.98 kW solar PV array (a fairly typical amount for a home solar install) could provide 72.2% of almost 10000 miles a year of driving directly.<br /><br />The feasibility of implementing this kind of variable rate smart charging on a household level with onsite solar pv needs a bit more investigation. The domestic charger on the nissan leaf can vary its charge rate in between 7A and 32A for the 6kW model or 7A and 13A for the 3kW model. Several people have already build open hardware variable rate electric car chargers making use of the fact that its possible to send a low voltage signal to an electric car to request a charge rate. Here are a couple of links to electric car charging related discussions and resources:<br /><br />Dod Davies solar charge controller <br /><a href="https://twitter.com/dodavies/status/541349518693117953">https://twitter.com/dodavies/status/541349518693117953</a><br /><br />OPenEnergyMonitor based electric vehicle charging<br /><a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/10805">http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/10805 </a><br /><br />Smart Charging a EVSE with OpenEnergyMonitor RF data, Working! <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/10805">http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/4930 </a><br /><br />Open EVSE:<br /><a href="https://code.google.com/p/open-evse/">https://code.google.com/p/open-evse/</a><br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ykLZpst1GRQ/VZVjKxJhAcI/AAAAAAAATSQ/YDrjYelhgQg/s1600/B4NCgt8IcAAOhDc.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="320" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ykLZpst1GRQ/VZVjKxJhAcI/AAAAAAAATSQ/YDrjYelhgQg/s320/B4NCgt8IcAAOhDc.jpg" width="240" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;From: <a href="https://twitter.com/dodavies/status/541349518693117953">https://twitter.com/dodavies/status/541349518693117953</a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />There are many aspects to consider and understand better when building a smart charger for electric vehicles for example it is suggested that to prolong the health of the battery its better to charge at a higher rate and up to the moment of starting your journey (rather than charge and let the battery sit at a high SOC). A more in depth understanding of the consequences of implementing this kind of charging and the balance point between battery life impacts and improved grid stability benefits or improved household economics would need to be understood.<br /><br />Another possibility is that an aggregate demand profile for charging hundreds of electric cars could generally fit a renewable energy availability profile through a mixture of a larger portion of fixed rate charging cars charging at times of high availability than at other times.<br /><br />In the next and final example in this zero carbon energy modelling series, we will combine the demand models for traditional electricity demand, electric heating and electric vehicles into one model and explore the implication of different electric vehicle demand profiles when interacting with multiple generation sources and multiple demand types.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hourly energy model example 5: Simple space heating model with heatpump's powered by renewable energy]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/06/hourly-energy-model-example-5-simple/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-22T10:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/06/hourly-energy-model-example-5-simple</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The 5th example in the online zero carbon energy modelling tool is where it starts to get more interesting: modelling the supply/demand matching between a variable renewable supply and space heating delivered by heatpumps. The electrification of heating with heatpumps so that heating can be supplied with renewable electricity is one of the key solutions used in ZeroCarbonBritain and <a href="http://withouthotair.com/c21/page_146.shtml.">Sustainable energy without the hot air.</a><br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-XQZc9Wcj3AU/VYfZ3abpxQI/AAAAAAAAS_A/cJgDAe0Sy6Q/s1600/heatingmodel.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="328" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-XQZc9Wcj3AU/VYfZ3abpxQI/AAAAAAAAS_A/cJgDAe0Sy6Q/s640/heatingmodel.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><b>Online tool:</b> <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel">http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel</a> &gt; navigate to <i>5. Variable supply and space heating demand</i><br /><br />The ZeroCarbonBritain dataset includes weighted daily temperatures for 10 years. This dataset can be combined with the solar dataset and a basic household energy model to create a seasonal heating demand model.<br /><br />Solar gains are an important aspect of space heating. Using <a href="http://github.com/emoncms/MyHomeEnergyPlanner">MyHomeEnergyPlanner</a> (The open source retrofit modelling tool we are developing with <a href="http://carbon.coop/">Carbon Coop</a>) to model a concept low energy house with fabric energy efficiency of 120W/K and a total of 16m2 of window area on a 80m2 (floor area) house with external surface area 206.4m2 the maximum potential annual solar gains where calculated to be 4429 kWh.<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-VgSn1d3RZv4/VYfW1wCB3LI/AAAAAAAAS-0/8_nSg_M_FkU/s1600/myhomeneergyplanner.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="342" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-VgSn1d3RZv4/VYfW1wCB3LI/AAAAAAAAS-0/8_nSg_M_FkU/s640/myhomeneergyplanner.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;MyHomeEnergyPlanner: http://github.com/emoncms/MyHomeEnergyPlanner &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;Running a low electricity demand of 2200 kWh a year and taking into account the solar gains. The space heating demand is only 4,247 kWh/year (compared to 13500 kWh/year for a typical house today a 68% space heating energy saving). If that remaining heat demand is supplied by a heatpump the electrical input should be 1,416 kWh/year. <br /><br /><b>Building an hourly space heating model:</b><br /><br />In order to calculate the space heating demand the model first calculates the total heating demand before solar gains and internal gains are taken into account. The space heating demand assumes constant internal temperature target of 18.5C rather than a morning and evening heating period. A further example with a higher internal temperature and variable profile would worth exploring for comparison. (21.0C being the passivhaus internal temperature target and there is an interesting discussion about the role of heating profiles, heatpump performance and demand spikes)<br /><br />The model then subtracts the internal gains (heat given off by appliances/cooking/lights etc) and the heat provided by solar gains through the windows, we use the solar pv capacity factor dataset here to provide our solar irradiance dataset. The amount of solar gain was scaled to match the amount of solar gain calculated in the SAP MyHomeEnergyPlanner tool based on the window orientations and areas – the total available solar gain energy is equivalent of 5.0 kW of solar pv.<br /><br />The model also keeps track of unused solar and internal gains when the internal temperature is already at the target temperature. The assumption at this point is that the excess heat is dumped outside perhaps through increased ventilation.<br /><br />The space heating demand after internal and solar gains are taken into account is then supplied with a heatpump with the simplifying assumption that the COP is constant and the heatpump fully responsive. A more complex model taking into account a degree of thermal mass in the building and the dynamics of the heatpump cross checked with real data would be useful here to check the assumptions taken in order to create an initial simplified model.<br /><br />Running the same fabric energy efficiency, max available solar gains and internal gains through this hourly model gives a space heating demand that is 14% higher than the space heating demand calculated with the SAP based MyHomeEnergyPlanner. The difference may be due to the differences in the way solar gains and internal gains utilisation is calculated in a monthly vs hourly model, further investigation is needed to fully understand the reason for this difference.<br /><br />Model heating demand results:<br />&lt;table class="table"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Total heat demand&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;8445 kWh/y&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;- Total utilized internal gains:&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2044 kWh/y of 2201 kWh/y&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;- Total utilized solar gains:&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1566 kWh/y of 4132 kWh/y&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;= Total space heating demand:&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;4835 kWh/y&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Total heatpump electricity demand:&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1611 kWh/y&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />Running the model for each renewable generation type to investigate the degree of direct supply demand matching we get the following results:<br /><br />&lt;table class="table"&gt;    &lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Onshore wind&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Offshore wind&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Wave&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Tidal&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td style="width: 12%;"&gt;Solar&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Installed capacity&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;0.568kW&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.383kW&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.651kW&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.776kW&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.95kW&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Percentage of demand<br />supplied directly&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;51%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;57%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;61%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;43%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;        &lt;td&gt;Percentage of time demand is<br />more or the same as the supply&lt;/td&gt;        &lt;td&gt;59%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;59%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;58%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;54%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;41%&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />Onshore, Offshore and Wave give quite similar levels of matching. Solar PV supplies the least demand because most of the solar electricity is generated in the summer and most of the heating demand is of course in the winter but also importantly when the sun is shining the heat demand is less due to direct solar gains, the dataset we are using for solar pv generation and solar gains is the same dataset.<br /><br />The online example also explores the effect of adding a very basic thermal store in order to increase the level of supply matching.<br /><br />The source code and datasets for the heating demand model and full supply/heating demand matching simulation is all open source available in both javascript and python.<br /><br />Space heating demand <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel/python/varsupply_spaceheatingdemand.py">varsupply_spaceheatingdemand.py</a> <br />Space heating demand with heatstore<a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel/python/varsupply_spaceheatingdemand_store.py">varsupply_spaceheatingdemand_store.py</a> <br />Full source code: <a href="https://github.com/TrystanLea/zcem">https://github.com/TrystanLea/zcem</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hourly energy model example 4: Complementarity of different renewable generating technologies]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/06/hourly-energy-model-example-4/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-18T07:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/06/hourly-energy-model-example-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We hear a lot that a renewable energy system benefits from having a mix of generating technologies. Combining wind and solar for example is said to provide a higher supply/demand matching than relying on one technology alone. When the wind isn’t blowing it may be sunny or vice versa.<br />How do we work out the best mix of different renewable generating technologies. When is it cheaper to add more wind than to add more solar, what is the balance point for a particular demand profile?<br /><br />This example explore’s the balance point for onshore wind + solar, both having large resource availabilities associated with them. The mix will be balanced based on energy cost. It would also be good to explore the balance based on embodied energy. As with all modelling based on costs the outcome will change as costs change, the important thing here is to understand the method so that we can explore for a given set of costs what the optimum mix might be.<br />In the recent contracts for a difference auction in the UK for renewable generation many of the onshore wind farms received a strike price of £82.50 per MWh. Two offshore wind projects received £115 per MWh and three solar farms received £79.23 per MWh. <br />Source: <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/407059/Contracts_for_Difference_-_Auction_Results_-_Official_Statistics.pdf">Contracts for Difference Auction Results</a><br /><br />In this example we will use these cost figures, the ZCB capacity dataset for onshore wind and solar and a simple flat demand profile.<br /><br />If we look at the results from example 2 investigating annual matching for wind and solar and add in the cost information:<br />&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;1.164kW of onshore wind delivers 3300 kWh/y at £272/y and a supply/demand matching of 65.88%.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;3.99kW of solar delivers 3300 kWh/y at £261/y and a supply/demand matching of 40.61%. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;One way to investigate the best mix is to fix the total annual energy cost and change the installed capacities of both solar and wind to achieve the greatest level of matching for a given energy cost. <br /><br />So lets take an annual energy cost of £272 and work out for this cost what is the maximum level of matching we can obtain from a wind + solar mix.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-zoor-og-PhQ/VYJx-BoKMCI/AAAAAAAASo0/OGcr5CPCxHA/s1600/windandsun.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="620" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-zoor-og-PhQ/VYJx-BoKMCI/AAAAAAAASo0/OGcr5CPCxHA/s640/windandsun.png" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /><b>Online tool:</b> <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel">http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel</a> &gt; navigate to <i>4. Mixed supply and flat demand</i><br /><br />&lt;table class="table"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Wind capacity&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Solar capacity&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Matching&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£272.02&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.1635&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;65.86 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£272.03&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.0235&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;70.04 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£272.03&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.9395&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.8&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;71.22 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£272.03&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.9115&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;71.33%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£272.04&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.8975&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.95&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;71.35%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£272.04&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.8835&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;71.34 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£272.04&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.8695&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.05&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;71.31 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£272.04&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.8555&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;71.26 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£272.04&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.8275&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;71.09%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />At an energy cost of £272/year a flat demand and the ZCB dataset we can see a clear benefit from combining solar and wind in the energy mix, increasing solar pv capacity appears to make sense up to 105.8% of installed wind capacity after which the matching starts to drop again for the given energy cost.<br /><br />Its important to note however that wind still provides the majority of the electricity at 2543 kWh of the 3300 kWh generated annually (76%). This is because of wind’s higher capacity factor in comparison with solar.<br /><br />How does the mix change if we decide to oversupply and pay a higher cost for the electricity. If we fix our annual cost to say £320<br /><br />&lt;table class="table"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Wind capacity&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Solar capacity&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Matching&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£320.06&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.369&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;69.88 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£320.07&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.229&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;73.98 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£320.08&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.144&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.8&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;75.20 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£320.08&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.089&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;75.44 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£320.08&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.075&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.05&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;75.45 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£320.08&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.061&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;75.44 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£320.08&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.047&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.15&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;75.41 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;£320.08&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.033&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;75.37 %&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />The maximum matching we obtained in this case happened where solar capacity was 97.7% of wind capacity.<br /><br />It appears that in these model runs, the optimal mix between solar and wind is to install an equal capacity of both, its interesting that this happens to be the case and that its not say half the wind capacity. The model results confirm the often discussed complementarity between solar and wind supply and that the benefit of their combination increases supply demand matching by around 5% points for no additional cost and is a similar scale of supply/demand matching improvement seen by increasing the oversupply of wind to 120% of demand but without the additional cost.<br /><br />Download python model:<br /><a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel/python/windandsun.py">http://openenergymonitor.org/energymodel/python/windandsun.py </a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
