<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: emonGLCD | Blog | OpenEnergyMonitor]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/categories/emonglcd/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-04T22:40:58+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Glyn Hudson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@openenergymonitor.zendesk.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Energy Display Options...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/03/energy-display-options/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-19T11:24:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2015/03/energy-display-options</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sadly as of last week we have run out of emonGLCD kits in the shop and have decided to discontinue the emonGLCD for the moment. Preparing the through-hole kits is very labour intensive and the time and skill required to solder assemble is lagging behind our other pre-assembled SMT units.<br /><br />Work has begun on a SMT pre-assembled replacement (<a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/5374">see forum thread</a>). However this would probably require significant investment in injection moulding tooling and commitment to high volume production. This would not would be a problem if we were sure on the design. However, I’m not sure if a standalone display is the right avenue to go down…<br /><br />I am aware there that there is certainly value in an ‘always on’ wall mount / coffee table energy display. Being able to easily glance at the display throughout the day when your home really does remind me to switch off lights and appliances when not in use. As well as checking everything is turned off (base level energy consumption) when leaving the house. An always on display gives users a ‘feel’ for how much energy various devices use as the display increases or decreases in real-time as a device is switched on or turned off.<br /><br />The future is mobile, everyone has at least one mobile device and increasingly as these devices are upgraded there are a large number of perfectly working just a bit slow older devices which could easily be given a second life as an energy display. This could help reduce the number of devices which end up being recycled or worse put into landfill, therefore helping to save energy in more ways the one! Old second hand Android phones or tablets can be picked up on Ebay for less than we could make an emonGLCD!<br /><br />I recently repurposed an old Nexus 7 tablet (2012 model) with a cracked screen as a home energy display displaying Emoncms MyElectric. I installed <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.nbondarchuk.android.keepscn&amp;hl=en">an app</a> to keep the screen on all the time when plugged in charging. The tablet uses 5W of power. An added advantage of using a mobile device as an energy display is they are ‘mobile’! The display can easily be moved around the house to support investigation power consumption of various appliances.<br /><br />Much work could be done on the software side to make a really nice packaged Android app for Emoncms which would support an energy display mode, useful features might be:<br /><br />&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Intelligent screen-on-off e.g the display could turn off at night, when energy falls to base level consumption indicating the house is unoccupied &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Using the tablets motion / proximity / light sensor to sense movement to turn screen on-off&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If device has an AMOLED display only certain pixels could be lit up to save power, like on the <a href="http://www.androidcentral.com/moto-x-best-feature-active-display">Moto-x Active Display </a>&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Auto start at startup and full screen mode &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Home screen widget to be used if user does not want to decicate a devices solely as an energy display or to be placed on current mobile home screen to enable quick checking of power consumption / temperature etc when out and about.    &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-CrEw0VbSe2Y/VQqrwBhpBZI/AAAAAAABF6A/LcUyS_41CF4/s1600/CAN-eRQWcAAP8y0.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-CrEw0VbSe2Y/VQqrwBhpBZI/AAAAAAABF6A/LcUyS_41CF4/s1600/CAN-eRQWcAAP8y0.jpg" height="426" width="640" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Emoncms MyElectric on Nexus 7 with cracked screen&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;<br />A super low power alternative could be to use an old e-reader with an E-ink display. Here’s Emoncms MyElectric running on a hacked Nook Touch.<br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-G1QTijq_mqA/VQqr710ke7I/AAAAAAABF6I/M4yq4Fwchtk/s1600/2014-11-13%2B08.10.28-1.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-G1QTijq_mqA/VQqr710ke7I/AAAAAAABF6I/M4yq4Fwchtk/s1600/2014-11-13%2B08.10.28-1.jpg" height="336" width="400" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;<span style="font-size: 12.8000001907349px;">Emoncms MyElectric on Nook Touch</span>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;Head over to the forums and let us know what you think…<br />&lt;div&gt;Discussion Thread: <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/10353">http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/10353</a>&lt;/div&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[emonGLCD V2 SMT Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/07/emonglcd-v2-smt-development/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-03T14:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2014/07/emonglcd-v2-smt-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For sometime now the emonGLCD has been lagging behind other OpenEnergyMonitor hardware units in terms of development, we’re still selling it only in thru-hole DIY kit form.<br /><br />We’ve been thinking about updating it to SMT pre-assembled for some time, however we’ve been dragged our heels somewhat since there has been thoughts that maybe a smartphone app could fill the same function. However I believe a physical LCD display unit fulfils a slightly different role to a smartphone app. I believe in certain circumstances there is certainly value to having an always-on low power LCD display located in a prominent location displaying current power consumption and or generation.<br /><br />I have found the emonGLCD with the ambient indication tri-colour LED’s to be a really useful easy-to-read indication of solar PV import / export at any given time.<br /><br />Doing a quick <a href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=emonglcd&amp;safe=off&amp;rlz=1CAACAG_enGB573GB573&amp;es_sm=93&amp;source=lnms&amp;tbm=isch&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=N1u1U42-KcXb7Abzk4CoDA&amp;ved=0CAkQ_AUoAg">Google search</a> shows that there are lots of emonGLCD being used and customized for all sorts of purposes we could not even have though of! For example: heat pump monitor, temperature measurements, electric car charge rate etc.<br /><br />With this in mind, we have decided to make an SMT version of the emonGLCD keeping the design largely the same (same LCD panel size and same controller chip ST7565). This will mean the current emonGLCD firmware sketches should run on the new unit with little or no modifications. <br /><br />I would be interested to heard your thoughts on what you would like in a new version of the emonGLCD?<br /><br />Over the past few weeks I’ve made a start to get a prototype, here is the main design criteria and features so far:<br />&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;  ST7565 128 x 64 LCD panel with integrated RGB backlight, <a href="http://www.vatronix.com/products/75.html">specifically this Vatronix unit</a> (to replace the LED’s on the current version)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;  Single front facing rotary encoder with push-to-select (to replace the three push buttons the the current)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;  Option for lithium battery pack with USB battery charging circuit and battery voltage monitor&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;  Arduino compatiable ATmega328 with RFM12B / RFM1269CW&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;  Option for on-board DS18B20 and DHT22 temperature and humidity sensors &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;Using SMT assembly and lower cost LCD unit and enclosure we should be able to reduce the price of the emonGLCD compared to the current version.<br /><br />Yesterday I sent off for the first prototype PCB revision:<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-YAr16KVXPrE/U7Vno3nIb4I/AAAAAAAA2zc/5Z419xiIra8/s1600/emonGLCD_V2.0_brd.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-YAr16KVXPrE/U7Vno3nIb4I/AAAAAAAA2zc/5Z419xiIra8/s1600/emonGLCD_V2.0_brd.png" height="526" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-VyOmm39X200/U7VnoxaukPI/AAAAAAAA2zg/MyAATsXtGtA/s1600/emonGLCD_V2.0_sch.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-VyOmm39X200/U7VnoxaukPI/AAAAAAAA2zg/MyAATsXtGtA/s1600/emonGLCD_V2.0_sch.png" height="522" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;<br /> <br /><br />&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-kyenCaUIo8Y/U7VnteHlIYI/AAAAAAAA2zw/L3pF1d4kAN8/s1600/2014-05-23+13.55.25.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-kyenCaUIo8Y/U7VnteHlIYI/AAAAAAAA2zw/L3pF1d4kAN8/s1600/2014-05-23+13.55.25.jpg" height="300" width="400" /></a>&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Testing the new LCD panel with built in RGB backlight&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;These images and more can be viewed in higher resolution in the emonGLCD V2 SMT Development album on G+, I will be periodically updating this album with development photos as things develop!<br /><a href="https://plus.google.com/photos/114424977493521882459/albums/6016575729643776881#">https://plus.google.com/photos/114424977493521882459/albums/6016575729643776881#</a><br /><br />&lt;h2&gt; <strong>Enclosure </strong>&lt;/h2&gt;The enclosure is an important part of the emonGLCD design considerations. We plan to move to a ‘proper’ custom made enclosure for the new emonGLCD. These are the main options available:<br /><br />1.) 3D printed (for small volumes and prototyping, not really possible for 500+ per production run)<br />2.) layered laser cut plywood or acrylic (like the Pimoroni Raspberry Pi cases)<br />3.) Injection molded plastic<br /><br />I’m specifically interested in exploring if/how an enclosure could be made with<strong> lowest embodied energy and maximum recyclability.</strong><br />We have not yet made much progress on case design nor have we got a designer or manufacturer in mind. If you would like to work with us please get in touch. Equally if you have some ideas on enclosure design I look forward to hearing.<br /><br />Please use the the emonGLCD V2 SMT forum thread for comments and discussion: <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/5374">http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/5374 </a><br /><br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[emonGLCD 433 / 868 Mhz RF Scanner & Signal Strength Meter ]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/08/emonglcd-433-868-mhz-rf-scanner-signal/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T14:27:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2013/08/emonglcd-433-868-mhz-rf-scanner-signal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/user/1824">Martin Roberts</a> has developed a fantastic bit of firmware for the emonGLCD to enable it to be used as an RF scanner and signal strength meter on the 433 / 868 Mhz RF band.<br /><br /> This makes the emonGLCD running this firmware a useful tool for debugging RF transmission and checking out signal strength.  To run the firmware a small hardware modification is required to the emonGLCD to access the analogue signal strength output signal from the RFM12B.<br /><br />Martin’s sketch has been added to the <a href="https://github.com/openenergymonitor/EmonGLCD/tree/master/GLCD_SSM">emonGLCD github repo</a>.<br /><br />Full details including build-guide and discussion can be found on the original <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/2395">forum thread</a>.<br /><br />&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-S0m9P9FKx18/UhtmSquXvUI/AAAAAAAAjn8/d7rcJjPtYM0/s1600/glcdssm_intf.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="300" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-S0m9P9FKx18/UhtmSquXvUI/AAAAAAAAjn8/d7rcJjPtYM0/s400/glcdssm_intf.jpg" width="400" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/sites/default/files/GLCD_SSM_interface.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="579" src="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/sites/default/files/GLCD_SSM_interface.jpg" width="640" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/sites/default/files/GLCD_SSM_inside.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="302" src="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/sites/default/files/GLCD_SSM_inside.jpg" width="400" /></a>&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;<br />&lt;/div&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Plug and play sensor nodes]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2012/08/plug-and-play-sensor-nodes/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-02T12:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2012/08/plug-and-play-sensor-nodes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;">At the moment to get a system up and running you need to do quite a bit of manual firmware configuration, setting&nbsp;unique&nbsp;node-id's selecting different emontx sketches for different functionality, hard coding the emonglcd to get different screens.&nbsp;To add a second emontx you need to add several lines of code to the emonbase and the basestation needs to know the data structure of the sensor nodes.</div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><br /></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-M15_WatZsbA/UBpruoqSO2I/AAAAAAAACeQ/DWmAsG4iG6c/s1600/OEM_system_emoncms2.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="212" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-M15_WatZsbA/UBpruoqSO2I/AAAAAAAACeQ/DWmAsG4iG6c/s400/OEM_system_emoncms2.png" width="400" /></a></div><br />What if you could upload a standard sketch to each of these nodes, plug your base station into your router, power up an emontx and see emontx 1 appear in a node list in emoncms. Then as you add more nodes they automatically appear in emoncms, no additional base station configuration needed. In time the software could develop to allow remote configuration of nodes such as&nbsp;emontx config and emonGLCD pages: beginning with page template functions as described in the last blog post:&nbsp;<a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2012/07/emonglcd-template-based-displays.html">emonglcd template based displays</a><br /><br />Continue reading the forum post <a href="http://openenergymonitor.org/emon/node/904">here</a>.
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[EmonGLCD Template based display's]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2012/07/emonglcd-template-based-displays/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-29T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.openenergymonitor.org/2012/07/emonglcd-template-based-displays</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div><div>I have been thinking about how it could be possible to program an EmonGLCD display remotely or at least specify which displays are shown i.e if you could construct a command to tell the display to:</div><div><br /></div><div><i>display solar pv page as page 1, use the solar power value from node 10.&nbsp;</i></div><div><i><br /></i></div><div>Skipping for now the how the commands are sent and interpreted, I think the first part of creating these specifiable displays is to convert the current display code into template functions which should be of benefit whether the displays are remotely programmed or not.</div><div><br /></div><div>Here's my first attempt at this:</div><div><br /></div><b>draw_power_page( "POWER" ,use, "USE", usekwh);</b><br /><div><b>draw_temperature_time_footer(temp, mintemp, maxtemp, hour,minute);</b></div><div>draws the following page:</div><div><br /></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-kdlCwY1w6Co/UBUIwPtRtNI/AAAAAAAACd4/3uUkU5CG3vA/s1600/IMAG0852.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-kdlCwY1w6Co/UBUIwPtRtNI/AAAAAAAACd4/3uUkU5CG3vA/s1600/IMAG0852.jpg" /></a></div><div><br /></div><div><br /></div><div><b>draw_solar_page(use, usekwh, gen, 2050, genkwh, temp, mintemp, maxtemp,&nbsp;hour,minute<span class="Apple-style-span">);</span></b></div><div><span class="Apple-style-span">draws:</span></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-oQkq7qv3I2I/UBUI5y7r0UI/AAAAAAAACeA/4MzulT2rkfc/s1600/IMAG0855.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-oQkq7qv3I2I/UBUI5y7r0UI/AAAAAAAACeA/4MzulT2rkfc/s1600/IMAG0855.jpg" /></a></div><div><span class="Apple-style-span"><br /></span></div><div>(thanks to drsdre for <a href="http://openenergymonitor.blogspot.com/2012/07/emonglcd-icons-by-drsdre.html">the icons!</a>)</div><div><br /></div><div>This is what the full code looks like:</div><div><br /></div><pre>#include&nbsp;&lt;JeeLib.h&gt;<br />#include&nbsp;&lt;GLCD_ST7565.h&gt;<br />#include&nbsp;&lt;avr/pgmspace.h&gt;<br />GLCD_ST7565&nbsp;glcd;<br /><br /><span style="color: #cc6600;">unsigned</span> <span style="color: #cc6600;">long</span> fast_update;<br /><br /><span style="color: #7e7e7e;">//&nbsp;Fixed&nbsp;values&nbsp;for&nbsp;this&nbsp;example</span><br /><span style="color: #cc6600;">double</span> temp = 17.4 ,maxtemp = 19 ,mintemp = 16;<br /><span style="color: #cc6600;">int</span> hour = 23, minute = 43;<br /><span style="color: #cc6600;">double</span> use = 252, usekwh = 2.5;<br /><span style="color: #cc6600;">double</span> gen = 1760, genkwh = 4.8;<br /><br /><span style="color: #cc6600;">void</span> <span style="color: #cc6600;"><b>setup</b></span>()<br />{<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;glcd.<span style="color: #cc6600;">begin</span>(0x20);<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;glcd.backLight(200);<br />}<br /><br /><span style="color: #cc6600;">void</span> <span style="color: #cc6600;"><b>loop</b></span>()<br />{<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #7e7e7e;">//-----------------------------------------------------------------------------</span><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #7e7e7e;">// Display update every 200ms</span><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #7e7e7e;">//-----------------------------------------------------------------------------</span><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #cc6600;">if</span> ((<span style="color: #cc6600;">millis</span>()-fast_update)&gt;200)<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;{<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;fast_update&nbsp;=&nbsp;<span style="color: #cc6600;">millis</span>();<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #cc6600;">int</span> S1 = <span style="color: #cc6600;">digitalRead</span>(15);<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #cc6600;">int</span> S2 = <span style="color: #cc6600;">digitalRead</span>(16);<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #cc6600;">int</span> S3 = <span style="color: #cc6600;">digitalRead</span>(19);<br /><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #cc6600;">if</span> (S1==1)<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;{<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #7e7e7e;">// powerstr, power, energystr, kwh</span><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;draw_power_page(&nbsp;<span style="color: #006699;">"POWER"</span> ,use, <span style="color: #006699;">"USE"</span>, usekwh);<br /><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #7e7e7e;">// temp, mintemp, maxtemp, hour, minute</span><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;draw_temperature_time_footer(temp,&nbsp;mintemp,&nbsp;maxtemp,&nbsp;hour,minute);<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;glcd.refresh();<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;}<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #cc6600;">else</span> <span style="color: #cc6600;">if</span> (S2==1)<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;{<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #7e7e7e;">// powerstr, power, energystr, kwh</span><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;draw_power_page(&nbsp;<span style="color: #006699;">"SOLAR"</span> ,gen, <span style="color: #006699;">"GEN"</span>, genkwh);<br /><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #7e7e7e;">// temp, mintemp, maxtemp, hour, minute</span><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;draw_temperature_time_footer(temp,&nbsp;mintemp,&nbsp;maxtemp,&nbsp;hour,minute);<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;glcd.refresh();<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;}<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #cc6600;">else</span><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;{<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span style="color: #7e7e7e;">// use, usekwh, gen, maxgen, genkwh, temp, mintemp, maxtemp, hour, minute</span><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;draw_solar_page(use,&nbsp;usekwh,&nbsp;gen,&nbsp;2050,&nbsp;genkwh,&nbsp;temp,&nbsp;mintemp,&nbsp;maxtemp,&nbsp;12,43);<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;glcd.refresh();<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;}<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;}&nbsp;<br />}<br /><br /><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: 'Times New Roman'; white-space: normal;">To run this you will need the accompanying icons and templates files, its all available in the EmonGLCD repo here:&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/openenergymonitor/EmonGLCD/tree/master/emonGLCD_Template_Dev">https://github.com/openenergymonitor/EmonGLCD/tree/master/emonGLCD_Template_Dev</a></span></pre><pre><br /></pre>Interested to hear any thoughts on how best to take this forward.</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
